. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY.
WELCOME TO THE JUNE 7TH JUNE 9TH, 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> YES, SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN
PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT SUPERVISOR WANG HUANG PRESENT
MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LONEY WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW MATERIALS MANY HAVE NEVER CEDED
LOST OR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL CARE TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
>> COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE SINCE THE REVIVAL ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I WANT TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY
KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? >> YES, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE
IN PERSON HERE IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER ROOM TWO
52ND FLOOR OF CITY HALL. WHEN YOU CAN'T BE HERE, THE
PROCEEDINGS ARE AIRING LIVE ON S.F. GOV TV'S LOCAL CABLE
CHANNEL OR LIVESTREAMING AT S.F. GOV TV DOT ORG.
YOU MAY SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING BY SENDING AN EMAIL
TO BOSSIE AT S.F. JOB TALK OR VIA U.S. POSTAL SERVICE TO THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN
FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION
FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT
OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE CONTACT THE
CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY
CALLING (415) 554-5184. FINALLY IN LINE WITH SUPERVISOR
FIELDER'S APRIL 7TH MEMO REQUESTING TO BE EXCUSED FROM
ALL MEETINGS UNTIL JUNE 30TH, A MOTION IS IN ORDER TO CONSIDER
THAT REQUEST FOR TODAY'S MEETING.
>> MEMBERS. MR. PRESIDENT, THAT CONCLUDES
MY COMMUNICATION. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAS INDICATED THAT HE IS COMING
BUT IS GOING TO BE LATE SO COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM THE MEETING ENTIRELY AND SUPERVISOR
DORSEY FROM THE VOTES THAT HE MISSES.
>> MOTION MADE BY FERRELL. VOTE BY FERRELL BY CHERYL YIKES
SORRY WRONG DISTRICT TWO MADE BY CHERYL AND SECONDED BY CHAN.
WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
WITHOUT OBJECTION. SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS EXCUSED
FOR THE DURATION OF THE MEETINGS TO PROVIDE SUPERVISOR
DORSEY UNTIL HE ARRIVES. >> AND THEN WITH THAT LET'S GO
TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER, MADAM CLERK.
>> THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS THE APPEARANCE BY THE
HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE. THERE BE NO QUESTIONS SUBMITTED
FROM ELIGIBLE MEMBERS REPRESENTING DISTRICTS FIVE
THROUGH EIGHT. THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD
FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES. >> WELCOME BACK TO THE CHAMBER,
MR. MAYOR. >> YOU MAY HAVE UP TO FIVE
MINUTES. THANK YOU.
BOARD PRESIDENT. LAST WEEK I SUBMITTED A
BALANCED BUDGET THAT IS FISCALLY RESPONSIBLE
AND STRENGTHENS OUR SOCIAL SAFETY NET.
SO EVEN IN THE FACE OF FEDERAL CUTS, SAN FRANCISCANS KNOW THEY
CAN COUNT ON THIS CITY. THIS BUDGET CLOSES A $642
MILLION TWO YEAR DEFICIT MOVING OUR CITY FORWARD FOR ALL SAN
FRANCISCANS. LAST JULY JUST AS OUR CITY WAS
GETTING BACK ON TRACK, THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT PASSED H.R.
ONE MAKING IT HARDER FOR PEOPLE ACROSS THIS COUNTRY TO ACCESS
THE CRITICAL HEALTH CARE AND FOOD ASSISTANCE THAT THEY
DEPEND ON. WHEN PEOPLE LOSE HEALTH CARE
COVERAGE, THEY TURN TO OUR PUBLIC HOSPITALS AND WHEN THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CUTS FUNDING THOSE COSTS FALL TO THE CITY OF
SAN FRANCISCO UNLESS WE HELP PEOPLE KEEP THE BENEFITS THEY
NEED, WE ARE DEDICATING $34 MILLION TO HELP SAN FRANCISCANS
STAY ON MEDI-CAL AND CAL FRESH. WE ARE HIRING 138 CASE MANAGERS
AND ELIGIBILITY WORKERS AT HSA TO HELP FAMILIES NAVIGATE THE
NEW REQUIREMENTS AND WE ARE COMMITTING $120 MILLION TO HELP
FAMILIES STAY HOUSED SO THAT ONE MISSED PAYCHECK OR
EMERGENCY MEDICAL BILL DOES NOT LEAD TO HOMELESSNESS.
>> THIS BUDGET PROTECTS LEGAL SERVICES FOR IMMIGRANT
FAMILIES. IT CONTINUES CRITICAL SUPPORT
FOR LGBTQ PLUS AND TRANS RESIDENTS INCLUDING CRITICAL
HIV HEALTH CARE SERVICES THAT WE HAVE NOW PROTECTED FOR TWO
CONSECUTIVE BUDGETS. THIS BUDGET ALSO ALLOCATES
FUNDING FOR A MODERNIZED FLEET OF POLICE CARS AND FIRE TRUCKS
TO KEEP OUR CITY SAFE. A NEW BACKUP SYSTEM THAT KEEPS
911 UP AND RUNNING DURING POWER OUTAGES AND A MAJOR INCREASE
IN STREET REPAVING AND POTHOLE REPAIR AND ALSO IMPORTANTLY
SECURITY IMPROVEMENTS AT OUR PUBLIC HEALTH FACILITIES SO
THAT OUR NURSES, OUR DOCTORS AND SOCIAL WORKERS ARE SAFE
WHILE THEY CARE FOR OTHERS. UNDER MY ADMINISTRATION WE WILL
NOT FALL BACK ON TEMPORARY FIXES THAT FORCED DEEPER CUTS
YEAR AFTER YEAR LAST YEAR IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THIS BOARD.
WE BEGAN MOVING BEYOND THAT CYCLE.
THIS BUDGET BUILDS ON THAT PROGRESS BY REDUCING OUR LONG
TERM STRUCTURAL DEFICIT BY APPROXIMATELY $300 MILLION.
AND OUR ADMINISTRATION HAS SAVED TAXPAYERS $100 MILLION
AND COUNTING BY SLOWING HIRING AND FOCUSING ON FILLING ROLES
THAT PROVIDE CORE SERVICES. BUT IF WE FAIL TO ACT NOW, OUR
STRUCTURAL DEFICIT WILL GROW TO $1 BILLION.
AND THE DIFFICULT CHOICES BEFORE US TODAY WILL BECOME
EVEN MORE PAINFUL AND COSTLY TOMORROW.
LAST YEAR WE INVESTED IN PUBLIC SAFETY AND TODAY CRIME
CONTINUES TO HIT RECORD LOWS. WE TRANSFORMED OUR HOMELESSNESS
RESPONSE AND NOW THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE SLEEPING ON OUR STREETS
IS AT THE LOWEST IT HAS BEEN IN 15 YEARS.
AND JUST TODAY WE ANNOUNCED THE MAY 2026 QUARTERLY COUNT FOUND
OUR CITY AT RECORD LOW NUMBER OF TENT ENCAMPMENTS ON OUR
STREETS FOR THE FOURTH TIME DURING THE LAST SIX MONTHS.
AND DOWN 53% SINCE WE TOOK OFFICE LAST JANUARY.
WE'RE ALSO AT RECORD LOW NUMBER OF LARGE VEHICLES ON OUR
STREETS AND 31% LOWER THAN JUST THIS PAST FEBRUARY.
MY PROPOSED BUDGET CARRIES THIS WORK FORWARD ENSURING THAT SAN
FRANCISCO'S SAN FRANCISCANS CAN AFFORD TO LIVE HERE.
BUSINESSES CAN GROW AND COMMUNITIES CAN THRIVE.
AND IN THE WEEKS AHEAD I LOOK FORWARD TO PARTNERING WITH YOU.
BOARD PRESIDENT MAILMAN BUDGET CHAIR CHAN, THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE AND THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO FINALIZE THIS
BUDGET. SAN FRANCISCO IS ON THE RISE
AND WE'RE NOT LEAVING ANYONE BEHIND.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COOPERATION AND COLLABORATION.
>> AND I'LL SEE YOU A LOT THIS MONTH.
THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR. I APPRECIATE YOU.
>> COLLEAGUES, THIS ITEM HAS BEEN DISCUSSED AND IS NOW
FILED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO BACK TO
OUR MEETING MINUTES. >> TODAY WE ARE APPROVING THE
BOARD MEETING MINUTES OF MAY 5TH 2026.
>> ALL RIGHT. CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY WALTON AND SECONDED BY CHAN
. >> AND MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MAHMUD MAHMUD I SUPERVISOR.
GENTLEMEN. ALL RIGHT, GENTLEMEN.
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WANG HUANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EITHER TEN TONIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED.
AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS
ONE THROUGH THREE ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN
ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
>> AND COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH
THREE SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDELMAN I AM I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION
THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FOUR.
>> ITEM NUMBER FOUR IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUSINESS
AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE TO EXTEND FOR TEN YEARS TO
DECEMBER 31ST 2035 AN EXEMPTION FROM THE PARKING TAX FOR A
LIMITED NUMBER OF SPECIAL PARKING EVENTS OPERATED BY
VOLUNTEER LED NONPROFIT ORGANIZATION ON SCHOOL DISTRICT
PROPERTY TO BENEFIT SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC SCHOOLS
IN EARNING LESS THAN 10,000 IN RENT PER EVENT.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FIVE.
>> ITEM NUMBER FIVE IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE 195
MILLION OF BOND PROCEEDS TO DPW REC AND PARK AND MTA FOR
ACQUISITION AND IMPROVEMENT OF REAL PROPERTY FOR VARIOUS
HEALTH CARE NURSING AND MENTAL HEALTH FACILITIES CERTAIN
TRANSPORTATION, PEDESTRIAN STREET SAFETY RELATED CAPITAL
IMPROVEMENTS, STREETSCAPE ENHANCEMENTS AND OTHER PUBLIC
SPACE IMPROVEMENTS AND RELATED COSTS IN FISCAL YEAR 2025, 2026
AND TO PLACE THESE FUNDS ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE THE SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
SIX THROUGH NINE TOGETHER. >> ITEM SIX THROUGH NINE ARE
FOR ORDINANCES REGARDING PC REVENUE BONDS AND AN
APPROPRIATION ITEM SIX APPROPRIATES ALL ESTIMATED
CAPITAL PROJECT RECEIPTS AND EXPENDITURES FOR THE PUC
FOR THE FISCAL YEAR ENDING JUNE 30TH 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028.
ITEM SEVEN AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF TAX EXEMPT
OR TAXABLE POWER REVENUE BONDS AND OTHER FORMS OF DEBT BY THE
PUC FOR 138.1 MILLION TO FINANCE A COSTS OF VARIOUS
CAPITAL PROJECTS BENEFITING THE POWER ENTERPRISE AND TO
AUTHORIZE THE ISSUANCE OF POWER REVENUE REFUNDING BONDS AND THE
RETIREMENT OF OUTSTANDING POWER ENTERPRISE COMMERCIAL PAPER
ITEM EIGHT AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF TAX EXEMPT
OR TAXABLE WASTEWATER REVENUE BONDS BY THE PUC FOR
APPROXIMATELY 1.1 BILLION TO FINANCE A COST OF VARIOUS
CAPITAL WASTEWATER PROJECTS BENEFITING THE WASTEWATER
ENTERPRISE AND TO AUTHORIZE THE ISSUANCE OF WASTEWATER REVENUE
REFUNDING BONDS AND THE RETIREMENT OF OUTSTANDING
WASTEWATER ENTERPRISE. COMMERCIAL PAPER AND ITEM NINE
AUTHORIZES THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF TAX EXEMPT OR
TAXABLE WATER REVENUE BONDS AND OTHER FORMS OF INDEBTEDNESS
BY THE PUC IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 570 MILLION TO FINANCE A COST OF VARIOUS
CAPITAL WATER AND HATCHERY WATER PROJECTS BENEFITING THE
WATER ENTERPRISE AND AUTHORIZING THE ISSUANCE OF
WATER REVENUE REFUNDING BONDS AND THE RETIREMENT OF
OUTSTANDING WATER ENTERPRISE COMMERCIAL PAPER SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER TEN. >> ITEM NUMBER TEN IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO ADJUST FEES CHARGED BY
THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTION AMENDING THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO ALLOW THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION AND PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO CHARGE NOTARY
FEES AND A FIRM TO SEEK DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 11. ITEM NUMBER 11 IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY NATASHA CORAL
AGAINST THE CITY FOR 150,000. THE LAWSUIT INVOLVES ALLEGED
PERSONAL INJURY ON A CITY SIDEWALK THE SAME HOUSE SAME
CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 12.
>> ITEM NUMBER 12 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE NORTH BEACH ENTERTAINMENT
ZONE THE FERRY BUILDING ENTERTAINMENT ZONE THE BUILDING
PLACE DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION ZONE TO AUTHORIZE THE OUTDOOR
CONSUMPTION OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE IS DURING AN
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE EVENT STARTING AT 11 A.M. RATHER THAN
NOON AND AFFIRMING THE SEQUEL DETERMINATION SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 13.
>> ITEM 13 IS AN ORDINANCE TO WAIVE THE COMPETITIVE
SOLICITATION REQUIREMENT UNDER ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER 21
G AND AUTHORIZING THE DIRECTOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
WORKS TO RETROACTIVELY ENTER INTO A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH THE
TRANSGENDER DISTRICT IN THE AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 24,000
FOR THE PURPOSE OF PRINTING AND INSTALLING PLACEMAKING
BANNERS IN THE TRANSGENDER DISTRICT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM 14.
>> ITEM 14 IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE
RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $1
MILLION GRANT FROM THE CALIFORNIA NATURAL RESOURCES
AGENCY FOR THE GENERAL FUND SPECIFIED GRANT FOR THE PROJECT
OF PORTSMOUTH SQUARE IMPROVEMENT PROJECT
AND APPROVING THE ASSOCIATED GRANT AGREEMENT FOR A TERM
LIMIT THAT IS EFFECTIVE UPON GRANT AGREEMENT EXECUTION
THROUGH MARCH 1ST, 2028. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
PLEASE CALL ITEMS 15 AND 16 TOGETHER.
>> ITEMS 15 AND 16 OR 2 RESOLUTIONS RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZING ACCEPT AND EXPAND GRANTS OR GIFTS OR THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT. ITEM 5015 EXECUTES AN AMENDMENT
TO THE GRANT AGREEMENT WITH THE BOARD OF STATE AND COMMUNITY
CORRECTIONS FOR THE ORGANIZED RETAIL THEFT PREVENTION GRANT
PROGRAM EXTENDING THE GRANT TERM FROM JUNE FIRST 2027
THROUGH JUNE 1ST, 2028 WITH NO CHANGE THE GRANT AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 15.3 MILLION AND ITEM 618 FOR AN IN-KIND
GIFT OF NALOXONE IN 2025 VALUED AT APPROXIMATELY 43,000 THROUGH
THE NALOXONE DISTRIBUTION PROJECT WHICH IS FUNDED BY THE
SUBSTANCE ABUSE AND MENTAL HEALTH SERVICES ADMINISTRATION
AND ADMINISTERED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE
SERVICES SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. PLEASE CALL ITEM 17.
>> ITEM 17 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE MODIFICATION NUMBER ONE
TO THE CONTRACT WITH CITY INFORMATION NETWORK COMPUTING
USA INC. FOR SUPPORT OF THE AIRPORT SHARED USE PASSENGER
PROCESSING SYSTEMS TO EXTEND THE TERM FOR THREE YEARS
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 AND INCREASE THE CONTRACT
AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY 9.7 MILLION FOR A NEW CONTRACT
AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 16.8 MILLION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 18.
>> ITEM NUMBER 18 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
AND AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY AND BEHALF OF THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO EXECUTE AN OFFICE LEASE FOR THE
CONTINUED USE OF OFFICE SPACE LOCATED AT 796 BRANDON STREET
WITH 796 BRANDON STREET LLC AS LANDLORD WITH AN ESTIMATED
COMMENCEMENT DATE OF JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2031
WITH TWO FIVE YEAR EXTENSION OPTIONS.
THE INITIAL TERM STARTING AT A MONTHLY BASE RENT OF
APPROXIMATELY 3000 WHERE TOTAL ANNUAL BASE RENT OF
APPROXIMATELY 41,000 WITH ANNUAL 3% INCREASES.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 19 ITEM 19 IS A RESOLUTION
TO AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ENTER INTO A
PERFORMANCE CONTRACT WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH
CARE SERVICES INCORPORATING THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES ACT
LETTERMAN PURCHASE SHORT ACT PROJECTS FOR ASSISTANCE
IN TRANSITION FROM HOMELESSNESS COMMUNITY MENTAL HEALTH
SERVICES BLOCK GRANT SUBSTANCE USE PREVENTION TREATMENT
AND RECOVERY SERVICES BLOCK GRANT AND CRISIS COUNSELING
ASSISTANCE AND TRAINING PROGRAM FOR THE PERIOD OF JULY 1ST 2026
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 20.
>> ITEM NUMBER 20 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AMENDMENT
NUMBER ONE TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND H AND WEST
SIDE COMMUNITY MENTAL HEALTH CENTER TO PROVIDE SHORT TERM
RESEARCH RESPITE BEDS PLUS HELP ESTABLISH STABILIZATION SUPPORT
FOR PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS TO EXTEND THE TERM
BY TWO YEARS FOR A NEW TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO
INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY 13.7 MILLION FOR
A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 21.5 MILLION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 21.
>> ITEM 21 IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE
OFFICE OF CANNABIS TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATELY 2.2
MILLION GRANT AWARD AND TO EXPEND INTEREST EARNED OR
ACCRUED ON GRANT FUNDS FOR THE GRANT TERM OF APRIL 1ST 2026
THROUGH JUNE THROUGH OCTOBER 31ST 2027 FROM THE GOVERNOR'S
OFFICE OF BUSINESS AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT FOR THE CANNABIS
EQUITY GRANTS PROGRAM FOR LOCAL JURISDICTIONS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> PLEASE CALL ITEM 22.
>> ITEM 22 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE ALL CITY DEPARTMENTS
TO SUBMIT APPLICATIONS FOR ALL GRANTS FUNDED BY THE 2024
CLIMATE BOND CALIFORNIA PROPOSITION FOUR FOR WHICH
THEY'RE ELIGIBLE. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEMS 23 AND 24 TOGETHER.
ITEMS 23 AND 24 TWO RESOLUTIONS REGARDING THE 820 POST STREET
HOUSING PROJECT ITEM 23 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
AND AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY AND MO CODE TO ENTER
INTO A GROUND LEASE FOR REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY
AND LOCATED AT 1820 POST STREET WITH GOLDEN GATE APARTMENTS LP
FOR A LEASE TERM OF 75 YEARS FOR AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF
15,000 IN ORDER TO REHABILITATE 100% AFFORDABLE 72 UNIT
MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING DEVELOPMENT FOR LOW INCOME
HOUSEHOLDS APPROVING AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR AND DIRECTOR OF EMOJI
CG TO EXECUTE AN AMENDED AND RESTATED LOAN AGREEMENT
AND TO PROVIDE THE BORROWER WITH A LOAN IN AN AGGREGATE
AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 22.6 MILLION TO FINANCE THE PROJECT
TO A FIRM SECURE DETERMINATION AND MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS AND WE CAN TAKE THESE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM 25. OH, I'M SORRY, MR. PRESIDENT.
I DIDN'T CALL ITEM 24 OH, WE CAN JUST TAKE ITEM 24.
IT IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE FOUR TO APPROVE FOR PURPOSES OF
THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE OF 1986 AUTHORIZING THE EXECUTION
AND DELIVERY OF A MULTI FAMILY HOUSING REVENUE NOTE IN AN
AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 18.7 MILLION FOR
THE PURPOSE OF PROVIDING FINANCE FOR THE REHABILITATION
OF A 71 UNIT MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING PROJECT LOCATED AT 1820
POST STREET. >> LET'S TAKE THAT ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
HAVING 25 ITEM 25 IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY
APPROVE AMENDMENT NUMBER FOUR TO A GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN O
IWD AND BAY AREA COMMUNITY RESOURCES FOR MANAGEMENT OF THE
COMMUNITY ECONOMIC RECOVERY HUB'S GRANT AND TO INCREASE THE
CONTRACT AMOUNT BY 1.5 MILLION FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 16.8 MILLION FOR THE PERIOD OF JULY 1ST 2022
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2026. >> SUPERVISOR CHANDA MANAV KAUL
AND SUPERVISOR WALDEN BEFORE I CALL ON YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON
THANK YOU SO MUCH MR. PRESIDENT.
I NEED TO RECUSE MYSELF FROM THIS ITEM DUE TO POTENTIAL.
>> CAN I HAVE OUR MOTION TO EXCUSE SUPERVISOR WALTON MOTION
BY SUPERVISOR CHAN SECONDED BY CHEN.
COLLEAGUES LET'S TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
SUPERVISOR WALTON IS EXCUSED. >> A AND SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, FIRST I WOULD LIKE TO THANK THE
BUDGET AND FINANCE COMMITTEE IN PARTICULAR CHAIR CHEN FOR
HEARING THIS ITEM AT LAST WEEK'S MEETING.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYSTS FOR
COORDINATING WITH O W D THE GRANTEE AND THE SUBCONTRACTORS.
THIS GRANT HAS FUNDED THREE COMMUNITY ECONOMIC RECOVERY
HUBS IN DISTRICT 910 AND 11. >> THIS HUBS OFFER SERVICES
RANGING FROM WORKFORCE REFERRAL JOB TRAINING FOR DISTRIBUTION
AND FLU SHOTS AND CONNECTION TO ESSENTIAL SOCIAL SAFETY
AND SOCIAL SAFETY NET SERVICES FOR MY DISTRICTS.
SPECIFICALLY CASA DE POYA HAS OFFERED NECESSARY LIFELINE
AND STABILIZATION TO RESIDENTS GIVEN THE LOCAL CHAOS OCCURRING
AT THE STATE AND FEDERAL LEVEL BETWEEN INCREASED IT ICE
ENFORCEMENT AND HR1 AND OTHER MASSIVE BUDGET CUTS TO OTHER
NECESSARY WRAPAROUND SERVICES IMPACTING THE MOST VULNERABLE
COMMUNITIES WE NEED TO PROTECT OUR LOCAL SERVICES HUBS THAT
KEEP OUR COMMUNITIES SAFE AND PROVIDE TRUSTED CONNECTION
TO NECESSARY SERVICES IN CULTURALLY AND LANGUAGE
COMPETENT WAYS. >> THE WORK THAT THIS GRANT
FUNDS IS ALSO IN ALIGNMENT WITH MANY OF OUR OTHER STATED
PRIORITIES. THE ITEM BEFORE YOU IS
RETROACTIVE GRANT AND MANY FOR SERVICES THAT HAVE ALREADY BEEN
GIVEN AND HAS ALREADY BEEN CONDUCTED DURING COMMITTEE
THERE WERE QUESTIONS FOR YET E W D ABOUT OVERSIGHT
AND REPORTING FROM THE PREVIOUS GRANTEE.
HOWEVER THE DEPARTMENT WILL BE STRENGTHENING ITS OVERSIGHT
MEASURES AND WILL WORK WITH THE CURRENT PROVIDER TO ACHIEVE THE
HIGHEST STANDARD FOR OVERSIGHT AND REPORTING.
AND I AM ASKING YOU TODAY MY COLLEAGUES TO APPROVE THIS TO
APPROVE THIS ITEM THIS TIME FUNDING THIS INCREDIBLY
IMPORTANT SERVICES. THANK YOU.
THANKS VIRGIN. LET'S TAKE THIS I HOPE WE HAVE
TO CALL THE ROLL PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 25 SUPERVISOR
DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
MANDOLIN HI BENJAMIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WONG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN SHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER OR NINE NICE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 26 ITEM NUMBER 26 IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO MAKE ADJUSTMENTS TO THE
BALBOA RESERVOIR SPECIAL USE DISTRICT THAT ALLOW FOR A
CONNECTING ELEMENT BETWEEN TWO BUILDINGS ADJACENT TO SOUTH
STREET AND ACROSS FROM THE BRIGHTON PASEO ESTABLISHING
CERTAIN DESIGN PARAMETERS AUTHORIZING RESIDENTIAL
AND CERTAIN OTHER USES AND ADOPTING A MAXIMUM HEIGHT
AT THIS LOCATION TO A FIRM SECURED DETERMINATION AND MAKE
THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 26
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISED HER MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MENDHAM AND I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER
AND ICE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 27 ITEM NUMBER 27 IS AN
ORDINANCE TO ACCEPT PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE ON GENEVA AVENUE
ASSOCIATED WITH THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT AT 2340 SAN
JOSE AVENUE ESTABLISHING AN OFFICIAL PUBLIC RIGHT AWAY WITH
AND STREET GRADE ACCEPTING A PUBLIC WORKS ORDER RECOMMENDING
VARIOUS ACTIONS REGARDING THE PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE WAIVE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER 23 AND AUTHORIZING AND INTO INTER
DEPARTMENT RENTAL TRANSFER CITY PRIVATE PROPERTY FROM MAUI TO
PUBLIC WORKS AND ADOPTING THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS TAKE THAT
SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING PLEASE CALL ITEM 28 ITEM NUMBER 28 IS
A RESOLUTION TO IMPOSE INTERIM INTERIM ZONING CONTROLS FOR 18
MONTHS TO REQUIRE A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR THE
ESTABLISHMENT OF A NEW CONVENIENCE STORE USES IN THE
TENDERLOIN AND SOUTH OF MARKET PUBLIC SAFETY ZONE TO A FIRM
SCORE DETERMINATION AND MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEMS 29 THROUGH 31 TOGETHER ITEMS 29
THROUGH 31 OR 3 RESOLUTIONS TO DETERMINE THAT THREE LIQUOR
LICENSE TRANSFERS WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC CONVENIENCE OR
NECESSITY OF THE CITY. ITEM 29 IS A PERSON TO PERSON
PREMISE TO PREMISES TRANSFER OF A TYPE 21 OFF SALE GENERAL BEER
WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR LICENSE TO HARLAN
RECORDS LLC DOING BUSINESS AS HARLAN WRECKERS LOCATED AT 447
BUSH STREET 18 HARLAN PLACE ITEM 30 IS A PERSON TO PERSON
PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER OF A DWIGHT TYPE 20 OFF SELL BEER
AND WINE LIQUOR LICENSE TO CASTRO BOTTLE SHOP INC DOING
BUSINESS AS CASTRO BOTTLE SHOP LOCATED AT 2306 MARKET AND 31
IS A PERSON TO PREMISE PREMISE TO PREMISES TRANSFER OF TYPE 48
ON SALE GENERAL PUBLIC PREMISES BEER WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS
LIQUOR LICENSE TO OATHS OF ART LLC DOING BUSINESS AS IN D
DARLENE LOCATED AT 537 STEPHENSON STREET WE TAKE THESE
SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 30 TWO ITEM 32 AS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE DOWNTOWN
HOSPITALITY ZONE IN THE AREA BOUNDED BY FIFTH STREET FROM
FOLSOM STREET TO MARKET STREET SEVERAL MAGNIN STREET FROM
MARKET STREET TO EDDY STREET EDDY STREET FROM ZERO MAGNIN
STREET TO MASON MASON STREET FROM EDDY TO ELLIS ELLIS STREET
FROM MASON STREET TO TAYLOR TAYLOR STREET FROM ELLIS TO
POST POST STREET FROM TAYLOR STREET TO MASON STREET MASON
STREET FROM POST TO BUSH BUSH FOR MASON TO KEARNY KEARNY FROM
BUSH TO MARKET MARKET FROM THIRD TO SECOND SECOND FROM
MARKET TO FOLSOM AND FOLSOM FROM SECOND TO FIFTH STREET
AND AFFIRMED TO SEQUEL DETERMINATION SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST
READING. >> AND WITH THAT LET'S GO TO
OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS,
OUR SPECIAL ORDER AT 230 IS THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS
TODAY. WE WILL BEGIN WITH DISTRICT SIX
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES
TODAY I AM HONORED TO RECOGNIZE KEN BUKOWSKI ON THE OCCASION OF
HIS RETIREMENT AFTER MORE THAN 24 YEARS OF DISTINGUISHED
SERVICE TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> HOW CAN YOU PERSONALLY THROUGHOUT HIS CAREER KEN HAS
BEEN KNOWN FOR HIS INTEGRITY, PROFESSIONALISM STEADY
LEADERSHIP AND HIS TRADEMARK DRY WIT.
HE HAS EARNED THE RESPECT OF COLLEAGUES ACROSS CITY HALL BY
APPROACHING EVERY CHALLENGE WITH THOUGHTFULNESS, PRAGMATISM
AND UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO PUBLIC SERVICE.
SINCE 2022, KEN HAS SERVED AS DIRECTOR OF THE CONVENTION
FACILITIES DEPARTMENT LEADING MOSCONE CENTER THROUGH A
PIVOTAL CHAPTER IN SAN FRANCISCO'S RECOVERY.
AS MANY OF YOU KNOW, MOSCONE CENTER IS THE ECONOMIC ENGINE
AT THE HEART OF DISTRICT SIX, THE DISTRICT I REPRESENT AND I
CANNOT THANK KEN ENOUGH FOR HIS LEADERSHIP AND COMMITMENT TO
OUR DOWNTOWN. AS THE CITY WORKED TO REBUILD
ITS TOURISM AND CONVENTION ECONOMY FOLLOWING THE PANDEMIC,
KEN HELPED TO CREATE THE MOSCONE CENTER RECOVERY FUND, A
$5 MILLION INITIATIVE THAT BROUGHT MAJOR CONVENTIONS
AND CONFERENCES BACK TO SAN FRANCISCO THAT HELPED TO
REVITALIZE OUR LOCAL ECONOMY AND THAT REAFFIRMED OUR
STANDING AS A PREMIER DESTINATION FOR VISITORS AROUND
THE WORLD. UNDER HIS LEADERSHIP, MOSCONE
CENTER SECURED AND RETAINED MAJOR EVENTS THAT INCLUDE THE
APEC LEADERS WEEK AND CEO SUMMIT, THE SUPER BOWL 60 FAN
EXPERIENCE THE NBA ALL STAR CROSSOVER EXPERIENCE MICROSOFT
IGNITE DATABRICKS DATA PLUS AI SUMMIT, DREAMFORCE AND MANY
MORE. THESE EVENTS GENERATED
SIGNIFICANT ECONOMIC ACTIVITY AND SUPPORTED LOCAL BUSINESSES
INCLUDING BUSINESSES AND DISTRICT SIX HOSPITALITY
WORKERS, HOTELS, RESTAURANTS AND NEIGHBORHOODS THROUGHOUT
SAN FRANCISCO CAN ALSO CHAMPIONED EFFORTS TO IMPROVE
THE AREAS AROUND MOSCONI CENTER PARTNERING WITH COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATIONS AND LEADERS TO BRING NEW LANDSCAPING, PUBLIC
ART MURALS AND OTHER BEAUTIFICATION PROJECTS TO
DOWNTOWN AND THROUGHOUT SOUTH MARKET.
HE UNDERSTOOD THAT CREATING A WELCOMING EXPERIENCE FOR
VISITORS ALSO MEANS INVESTING IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS THEY
EXPERIENCE WHEN THEY ARRIVE BEFORE LEADING THE CONVENTION
FACILITIES DEPARTMENT, KEN SERVED IN NUMEROUS LEADERSHIP
ROLES ACROSS CITY GOVERNMENT INCLUDING DEPUTY CITY
ADMINISTRATOR AND CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER, INTERIM
DIRECTOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF TECHNOLOGY AND CHIEF FINANCIAL
OFFICER FOR BOTH THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT
AND THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN YOUTH AND THEIR FAMILIES.
HE ALSO PLAYED A KEY ROLE IN THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE
PERMIT CENTER AT 49 SOUTH VAN NESS HELPING TO CREATE A ONE
STOP DESTINATION THAT HAS IMPROVED ACCESS TO CITY
SERVICES FOR RESIDENTS AND BUSINESSES ALIKE BEFORE
ENTERING CITY GOVERNMENT CAN ALSO SERVED AS EXECUTIVE
DIRECTOR OF POSITIVE RESOURCE CENTER, AN ORGANIZATION THAT I
HAVE ENORMOUS RESPECT AND AFFECTION FOR.
THERE HE HELPED TO EXPAND EMPLOYMENT AND BENEFIT SERVICES
FOR PEOPLE LIVING WITH HIV AIDS AND HE MADE A MEANINGFUL
DIFFERENCE IN THE LIVES OF COUNTLESS SAN FRANCISCANS.
IT IS ESPECIALLY FITTING THAT KEN'S RETIREMENT COMES AS WE
CELEBRATE PRIDE MONTH AS A FELLOW MEMBER OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY AND THROUGH HIS YEARS
OF SERVICE INSIDE AND OUTSIDE OF CITY GOVERNMENT HE HAS
HELPED TO ADVANCE THE VALUES OF INCLUSION, DIGNITY, OPPORTUNITY
AND YES, PRIDE THAT MAKE OUR CITY STRONGER.
KEN'S LEGACY CAN BE SEEN IN THE INSTITUTIONS HE HAS
STRENGTHENED THE PROJECTS HE HELPED TO DELIVER AND THE
COUNTLESS PEOPLE WHOSE LIVES AND CAREERS HE TOUCHED ALONG
THE WAY. KEN.
ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, THANK YOU FOR YOUR
EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO TO ITS PEOPLE AND TO ITS VISITORS ALIKE.
AND CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT.
MAYOR NOW PEOPLE, BEFORE YOU SPEAK I KNOW CITY ADMINISTRATOR
CARMEN CHU AND DEPUTY CITY ADMINISTRATOR RACHEL SUE KERMAN
WOULD LIKE TO EXPRESS THEIR CONGRATULATORY REMARKS AS WELL.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. I AS YOU CAN SEE WITH KEN, HE
DID NOT WANT THAT PUBLIC APPLAUSE SO I THINK WE SHOULD
GIVE HIM ANOTHER ONE. >> I KNOW THAT WE'RE WE WILL
MISS KEN. KEN HAS SERVED SAN FRANCISCO
VERY WELL FOR THE LAST 25 YEARS IN VARIOUS ROLES AT DCF AS
DEPUTY CITY ADMINISTRATOR AND NOW AS THE EXECUTIVE
DIRECTOR OF THE MOSCONE CONVENTION CENTER.
AND I SIMPLY WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE HIS FAMILY WHO IS
HERE, PETER WHO IS HIS HUSBAND AND HIS SON JOSE WHO IS HERE.
>> THANK YOU. >> THEY SHARE THEY SHARE HIS
LIFE WITH US AND WE WANT TO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR LETTING
US HAVE A LITTLE MOMENT OF HIS TIME TO BE ABLE TO SERVE THE
PUBLIC. I KNOW THAT I WILL SHARE
AND CEDE MY TIME TO RACHEL ZUKERMAN, MY DEPUTY DIRECTOR
WHO IS ALSO GOING TO SAY A FEW WORDS BUT KEN FROM THE BOTTOM
OF MY HEART I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE.
WE WILL MISS YOU AND YOUR VERY CAPABLE AND QUIET DEMEANOR
WHICH HONESTLY IS A LITTLE BIT DISCONCERTING BUT REALLY
EFFECTIVE. >> HI RACHEL SILVERMAN I'M A
DEPUTY CITY ADMINISTRATOR AND I'VE HAD THE PLEASURE OF
GETTING TO WORK WITH KEN FOR THE 18 PLUS YEARS THAT I'VE
BEEN WITH THE CITY AND WE'VE ALWAYS BEEN ABLE TO WORK
TOGETHER IN VARIOUS ROLES THROUGHOUT OUR CAREERS AND THE
ONE THING THAT HAS REMAINED CONSISTENT THROUGHOUT IS THE
AMOUNT OF TIME AND GENEROSITY SPENT WITH ME AND HIS
COLLEAGUES WHEN THINKING THROUGH COMPLEX SITUATIONS THAT
THE CITY HE HAS AN UNBELIEVABLE AMOUNT OF INSTITUTIONAL
KNOWLEDGE AND IS ALWAYS WILLING TO SHARE IT AND I REALLY WANT
TO THANK HIM FOR THAT TIME AND YOUR EXPERTISE AND I'M
GOING TO REALLY MISS CALLING ON YOU.
I'M EXCITED FOR YOU IN THIS NEXT PHASE BUT WE WILL
DEFINITELY MISS YOU. >> SO CONGRATULATIONS.
THANK. >> SO KEN BUKOWSKI THE FLOOR IS
YOURS. OKAY, I'LL KEEP IT.
I'LL KEEP IT BRIEF. FIRST OF ALL, THANK THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD FOR THIS
RECOGNITION. IT'S NICE TO BE IN THIS
CHAMBERS AND GETTING SOMETHING RATHER THAN WORRYING ABOUT THE
BOARD TAKING SOMETHING DURING A BUDGET HEARING WHICH IS HOW I
SPENT MOST OF MY CITY CAREER PARTICULARLY IN CFO ROLES THAT
USUALLY STANDING UP HERE WAS A TERRIFYING EXPERIENCE.
IT STILL IS A LITTLE BIT TODAY QUITE HONESTLY.
>> BUT I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY HUSBAND PETER IN SAN JOSE AS AS
CITY ADMINISTRATOR TOO. DID ANY OF YOU HAVE FAMILY KNOW
THAT THEY ARE REALLY THE ONES THAT SUPPORT YOU AND ALLOW YOU
TO DO YOUR WORK HERE WHETHER IT'S IN THIS JOB OR ANY JOB
AND WITHOUT THEM I REALLY COULDN'T HAVE DONE WHAT I'VE
BEEN ABLE TO DO FOR THE CITY. SO THANK YOU.
>> AND I THINK THE ONLY OTHER THING I WANT TO SAY IS JUST TO
ALSO ACKNOWLEDGE I KNOW YOU YOU'LL BE RECOGNIZED AND A FEW
OTHER PEOPLE TODAY AS WELL. BUT THERE ARE PROBABLY HUNDREDS
OF OTHER CITY EMPLOYEES RETIRING THIS MONTH.
AND SO I JUST WANT TO RECOGNIZE ALL OF THE WORK THAT THEY DO AS
WELL. THEY MAY NOT ALWAYS GET THE
ACCOLADES THE CUSTODIANS, THE SENIOR ACCOUNT CLERKS, THE
FLEET ENGINEER FOLKS BUT THEY ARE CRITICAL TO THE WORK WE DO
EVERY DAY AND SO I DO THIS WORK AND I ENJOY BEING IN PUBLIC
SERVICE. I LOVE SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS IS MY HOME. I SAY IT NOW SECOND SAID BEFORE
WE ARE BUT I EVERYONE KNOWS I HAVE A BIAS OF HIRING PEOPLE
WHO ACTUALLY LIVE IN THE CITY BECAUSE I BELIEVE THAT'S
IMPORTANT TO LIVE IN THE CITY THAT YOU'RE SERVING AND SO I
ENJOY WALKING TO AND FROM WORK .
I LOVE THIS CITY. I THINK IT'S THE BEST CITY
IN THE WORLD AND SO I LOOK FORWARD TO FINDING OTHER WAYS
TO SERVE IT IN THE FUTURE AND MAYBE COMING BACK TO THIS
BOARD AND IN SOME POINT IN SHARING MY FEELINGS ABOUT
DIFFERENT ISSUES. >> BUT I JUST WANT THANK YOU
AGAIN FOR THIS RECOGNITION AND THANK YOU FOR THE
OPPORTUNITIES AND THE LEARNING TYPE YOU DON'T HAVE IN THIS
ROLE. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY YOU WANT TO BRING DIRECTOR BORKOWSKI INTO
THE WELL
YOU ONE THANK YOU. SO OUTSIDE DISTRICT TWO
SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDEL MANDOLIN
COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE VIRGIN DONAHUE
VIRGINIA WOULD YOU PLEASE COME UP TO THE LECTERN?
THIS IS THIS IS BOTH A SAD DAY AND AN EXCITING DAY.
A SAD DAY BECAUSE AFTER 11 YEARS OF LEADERSHIP, EXECUTIVE
DIRECTOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL
VIRGINIA IS STEPPING DOWN AFTER SERVING THE ANIMALS AND THE
PEOPLE OF THIS CITY WITH COMPASSION, INTEGRITY
AND UNWAVERING DEDICATION. >> WE ARE VERY SAD TO SEE YOU
GO BUT IT'S ALSO EXCITING. BUT I'LL GET TO THAT LATER.
BEFORE JOINING ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL, VIRGINIA CO
FOUNDED PET CAMP, A PET LODGING FACILITY WITH TWO LOCATIONS
AND 40 EMPLOYEES. VIRGINIA ALSO SERVED
IN MANAGEMENT ROLES IN PUBLIC AFFAIRS AT THE ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION AGENCY AND BOTH CHICAGO AND SAN FRANCISCO.
AND SHE HOLDS A BACHELOR'S IN JOURNALISM AND A MASTER'S
IN MANAGEMENT FROM NORTHWESTERN.
NOW UNDER VIRGINIA'S LEADERSHIP, ANIMAL CARE
AND CONTROL HAS BECOME ONE OF THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE OPEN
DOOR SHELTERS IN THE COUNTRY ACCEPTING EVERY ANIMAL
REGARDLESS OF SPECIES MEDICAL CONDITION OR BEHAVIOR
AND RESPONDING TO NEARLY 10,000 ANIMALS AND 12,000 CALLS FOR
HELP EVERY YEAR. THE DEPARTMENT ALSO PROVIDES
EMERGENCY SHELTER FOR APPROXIMATELY 400 PETS EVERY
YEAR WHEN THEIR OWNERS ARE FACING HOSPITALIZATION,
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE OR INCARCERATION.
AND THIS IS INDEED A REFLECTION OF VIRGINIA'S BELIEF THAT
ANIMAL WELFARE AND HUMAN WELFARE ARE INSEPARABLE.
>> IN 2021, VIRGINIA LED EC'S SUCCESSFUL TRANSITION INTO THE
NEW MODERN AND SEISMICALLY SAFE FACILITY AT 1419 BRYANT STREET.
AND SHE THEN STRENGTHENED THE DEPARTMENT'S ROLE AS THE CITY'S
FIRST RESPONDER FOR ANIMALS DURING DISASTERS.
WILDLIFE SINCE THE INCIDENTS AND CRUELTY INVESTIGATIONS,
VIRGINIA EMBODIES COLLABORATIVE LEADERSHIP WHILE DIRECTOR SHE
EXPANDED THE COMMUNITY PARTNERSHIPS OFFERING LOW COST
VETERINARY CARE, PET FOOD ASSISTANCE, VACCINATIONS
AND MICROCHIPPING AND GROUP PROGRAMS THAT KEEP PETS
AND THEIR OWNERS TOGETHER THROUGH HARDSHIP.
NOW I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THAT VIRGINIA DID NOT DO THIS
ALONE BUT WAS THE LEADER OF A FANTASTIC SCC TEAM SOME OF WHOM
ARE HERE TODAY JUST IN ALBERTO ARIANA LUCHSINGER, SB BARTOLO
JUDY CHOI HOLLY STUMP IN AND WE WELCOME AMY CORSO WHO WILL BE
STEPPING IN AS THE NEXT EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR VIRGINIA
WHILE WE WILL ALL MISS YOUR STEADY AND COMPASSIONATE
LEADERSHIP I KNOW YOU ARE LEAVING THE DEPARTMENT IN VERY
GOOD HANDS. NOBODY DOES PUBLIC SERVICE
ALONE AND NOT ONLY IS IT ABOUT COLLEAGUES, IT'S ALSO ABOUT
FAMILY. SO VIRGINIA, THEY ALSO LIKE TO
ACKNOWLEDGE YOUR FAMILY HERE TODAY I BELIEVE THAT YOUR
HUSBAND MARK AND YOUR DAUGHTERS JOANNA AND SIDNEY ARE HERE
TODAY. >> AND THEN ALSO I THINK
CLEMENT AND QUINN ARE NOT HERE BUT THEY ALSO DESERVE GREAT
RECOGNITION. >> AND SO TO VIRGINIA'S FAMILY
IT IS YOUR SUPPORT THAT MAKES VIRGINIA'S LEADERSHIP POSSIBLE
AND WE ARE ALL GRATEFUL ALL FOR YOU GIVING HER TO US AND TO
THIS CITY. >> NOW FINALLY I WANT TO
RECOGNIZE DEPUTY CITY ADMINISTRATOR JENNIFER JOHNSON
FOR BEING HERE TODAY. THANK YOU FOR BEING A COMMITTED
PARTNER WITH VIRGINIA AND IN MAKING A LIFE SAVING WORK
POSSIBLE. NOW BACK TO THE EXCITING PART.
WHILE WE WILL MISS YOU AS HEAD OF HCC, WE ARE EXTREMELY GLAD
THAT YOU ARE STAYING IN SAN FRANCISCO IN YOUR NEXT CHAPTER
AS THE HEARING OFFICER FOR SPD'S VICIOUS AND DANGEROUS DOG
HEARINGS. >> THANK I YOU WILL BE YOU WILL
BE THE DOG JUDGE FOR DOG COURT .
NOW I WANT TO CLARIFY THAT IT IS OFFICIAL THAT THE DOG JUDGE
IS NOT IN FACT A DOG BUT IS A HUMAN IN CASE THERE WAS ANY YOU
KNOW BUT BUT IN ALL SERIOUSNESS, WE'RE REALLY QUITE
THRILLED YOU'LL BE TAKING UP THIS MANTLE AND HELPING THESE
CRITICAL HEARINGS GET BACK ON TRACK.
>> AND IN A MOMENT WE WOULD LOVE TO HEAR FROM YOU BUT ON
BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS VIRGINIA, THANK YOU
SO MUCH FOR EVERYTHING YOU HAVE GIVEN TO THIS CITY'S ANIMALS,
FAMILIES AND COMMUNITIES. WE WISH YOU ALL THE BEST.
BUT BEFORE YOU SPEAK, THERE'S SOMEBODY BEHIND YOU WHO VERY
MUCH WANTS TO SAY A FEW WORDS. >> SO I'D LIKE TO WELCOME CITY
ADMINISTRATOR CARMEN CHU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH,
SUPERVISOR. YOU HAVE DONE SUCH A THOROUGH
JOB. EXPLAIN ALL OF THE
CONTRIBUTIONS THAT VIRGINIA HAS SHARED THAT I DON'T HAVE TOO
MUCH MORE TO ADD EXCEPT TO ADD MY PROFOUND THANKS TO YOU
AND TO YOUR FAMILY. SHE IS SOMEONE WHO HAS BEEN A
TREMENDOUS ADVOCATE, THE ULTIMATE PROFESSIONAL AND SO WE
WILL MISS WORKING WITH VIRGINIA AND AS YOU SAW AS YOU MENTIONED
HER NEXT LIFE COMING BACK WORKING WITH VICIOUS DOGS
OFTENTIMES PEOPLE WHO TAKE ON THESE JOBS DO IT BECAUSE OF
THEIR LOVE FOR PUBLIC SERVICE AND THAT PUBLIC SERVICE
AND LOVE FOR PUBLIC SERVICE CONTINUES EVEN AFTER RETIREMENT
. >> SO I WANT TO THANK HER FOR
THAT. I DO WANT TO SHARE MY TIME WITH
DEPUTY CITY ADMINISTRATOR JENNIFER JOHNSON WHO HAS HAD
THE HONOR OF WORKING WITH HER MANY, MANY YEARS AND I WANT TO
MAKE SURE TO GIVE HER AN OPPORTUNITY TO SAY SOMETHING
WONDERFUL. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISORS.
IT'S VERY MUCH MY PLEASURE TO SAY A FEW WORDS ABOUT VIRGINIA
A VERY QUICKLY BECAUSE I KNOW WE'RE SHORT ON TIME.
>> I'VE HAD THE PLEASURE OF WORKING WITH VIRGINIA FOR OVER
THE LAST SIX YEARS. I AM SINCERELY GOING TO MISS
HER. SHE IS A NO NONSENSE STEADY,
DIRECT AND STRATEGIC APPROACH. >> SHE IS THE MOST UNFLAPPABLE
AND DETERMINED PERSON YOU WILL EVER MEET EVEN IN THE MOST
EXTRAORDINARY CHALLENGES CHAOTIC EMERGENCIES AND OFTEN
COMPLICATED AND EMOTIONALLY CHARGED AND SENSITIVE ISSUES.
SHE IS AN UNWAVERING LEADER IN ALL THINGS SO SHE HAS LEFT A
LASTING MARK ON OUR CITY AND SHE HAS IMPROVED THE
OUTCOMES FOR OUR FAMILIES AND OUR ANIMALS AND THEIR PETS
SO I OWE YOU A DEBT OF GRATITUDE FOR EVERYTHING THAT
YOU HAVE DONE AND FOR YOUR PATIENCE WITH ME.
I'VE CERTAINLY LEARNED A LOT AND I TOO AM A LITTLE AFRAID OF
YOUR CALM STILLNESS AND YOUR YOUR AIR CALM DEMEANOR ALL THE
TIME. >> ANYWAY, THANK YOU.
>> I'M GOING TO JUMP IN AS WELL BECAUSE I THINK THAT THE VISION
DONAHUE IS MY CONSTITUENT STILL IS STILL MY CONSTITUENT.
ALL RIGHT, DISTRICT EIGHT YOU WILL ALL EXCELLENT.
>> I GOT TO KNOW WELL, I GOT I BENEFITED FROM VIRGINIA DONAHUE
BEFORE I MET VIRGINIA DONAHUE BECAUSE I THERE ARE TWO OF US
ON THIS BOARD I THINK WHO TOOK OFFICE AFTER HAVING BEATEN
INCUMBENTS AND THE THE THE MOOD THE TRANSITION IS NOT ALWAYS AN
EASY ONE AND I BENEFITED FROM AN INTERN WHO HAD BEEN IN THE
PRIOR SUPERVISORS OFFICE AND WAS WILLING TO STAY THROUGH
INTO MY OFFICE AND I THINK THAT WITHOUT QUINN WE WOULD HAVE HAD
NO IDEA WHAT TO DO. SO I DO WANT TO THANK FOR
JEANNIE DONAHUE FOR FOR GIVING JEFF SHEEHY AND THEN ME QUINN
AND THEN I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR ENDLESS PATIENCE WITH
MY QUESTIONS OVER ALL THESE YEARS, YOUR ENDLESS PATIENCE
WITH ALL THE THINGS THAT THE DIRECTOR OF ANIMAL CARE
AND CONTROL HAS TO DEAL WITH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND FOR THE EXTRAORDINARY LEADERSHIP THAT
YOU'VE SHOWN IT'S BEEN A PLEASURE TO WORK WITH YOU
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CONGRATULATE ASIANS ON SOLVING
THE VICIOUS AND DANGEROUS DOG PROBLEM.
AMAZING. AND THANK YOU VIRGINIA DONAHUE
FOR PLAYING A ROLE IN THAT. >> ALL RIGHT.
THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> THANK YOU.
I'M HAPPY SORT OF HAPPY TO DO THE VICIOUS AND DANGEROUS DOG
HEARING PROCESS BECAUSE IT REALLY, REALLY HAS TO HAPPEN
AND IT'S IT'S TRULY IMPORTANT REALLY WHO I WANT TO THANK
TODAY ARE MY COLLEAGUES. SUPERVISOR CHERYL HAS
ELOQUENTLY EXPLAINED WHAT THEY DO BUT I CAN'T STRESS ENOUGH
HOW PHYSICALLY DEMANDING AND EMOTIONALLY CHALLENGING
THEIR WORK IS. THEY CARE FOR 10,000 ANIMALS A
YEAR AND GENERALLY IF AN ANIMAL COMES TO THE SHELTER IT IS NOT
HAVING A GOOD DAY AND THE TEAM IS ALWAYS GRACIOUS.
>> THEY ARE PROFESSIONAL, THEY ARE ON TOP OF IT.
YOU CAN REST ASSURED THAT THEY ARE DOING EVERYTHING THEY CAN
POSSIBLY CAN FOR THE ANIMALS AND THEIR PEOPLE.
SINCE THE PANDEMIC THE NUMBER OF ANIMALS WE HAVE IN THE
CUSTODY PROGRAM WHICH IS THE PROGRAM FOR FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE
INCARCERATED OR EVICTED OR VICTIMS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
ARE HOSPITALIZED THAT ROLLED AROUND FOR DECADES AT 500 PER
YEAR SINCE THE PANDEMIC IT'S JUMPED TO A THOUSAND.
>> THAT IS AN ENORMOUS BURDEN AND RIGHT NOW IT'S HAVING THE
BIGGEST EFFECT ON OUR CITIES DOGS.
IT HAS BECOME HARDER AND HARDER TO FIND NEW HOMES FOR THEM
AND A RESULT AS A RESULT MORE ARE BEING EUTHANIZED.
WE'RE IN THE MIDST OF WORKING WITH UC DAVIS ON A SEARCH FOR
SOLUTIONS BUT THERE ARE MORE WAYS THAT THE PUBLIC CAN HELP
NOW IF YOU'RE LOOKING FOR AN ANIMAL COMPANION PLEASE MAKE
YOUR FIRST STOP ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL EVEN IF YOU
ULTIMATELY FIND YOUR NEW BEST FRIEND SOMEWHERE ELSE, LOOK AT
YOUR CITY ANIMAL SHELTER FIRST. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL WOULD YOU LIKE TO BRING THE DIRECTOR INTO
THE WELL? YEAH, I HEAR
. >> NEXT UP DISTRICT SEVEN
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
IF WE COULD HAVE A SAJA AND CHUCK BUTLER PLEASE COME
FORWARD. I LIKE THE WAY THAT SOUNDS.
>> COME ON UP, PLEASE. TODAY I AM HONORED TO RECOGNIZE
DUKE BUTLER FOR HIS OUTSTANDING SERVICE TO THE RESIDENTS OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND IN PARTICULAR THE COMMUNITY SERVED BY A TERRIBLE
STATION SO EVERYBODY CAN RELAX PARTICULARLY YOU AS SUPERVISOR
CHEN. SERGEANT BUTLER IS NOT LEAVING
US OR RETIRING. HE HAS BEEN PROMOTED.
CONGRATULATIONS. YOU SERGEANT BUTLER'S STORY IS
ONE OF PERSEVERANCE, RESILIENCE AND DEDICATION AFTER
IMMIGRATING TO SAN FRANCISCO FROM LIBERIA AS A CHILD HE
BUILT A SUCCESSFUL CAREER IN THE PRIVATE SECTOR BEFORE
ANSWERING A HIGHER CALLING AND JOINING THE SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT. >> HIS JOURNEY REMINDS US THAT
PUBLIC SERVICE IS NOT JUST A PROFESSION IT IS A COMMITMENT
TO MAKING A DIFFERENCE IN THE LIVES OF OTHERS.
THROUGHOUT HIS YEARS AT TERRIBLE STATION, SERGEANT
BUTLER HAS EXEMPLIFIED THE VERY BEST OF COMMUNITY POLICING
WHETHER WALKING A FOOT BEAT, RESPONDING TO CALLS FOR SERVICE
OR SIMPLY GREETING NEIGHBORS WITH HIS TRADEMARK SMILE.
HE HAS CONSISTENTLY DEMONSTRATED THAT EFFECTIVE
POLICING BEGINS WITH RESPECT WITH COMMUNICATION WITH A
GENUINE HUMAN CONNECTION. I HAVE A WHOLE COLLECTION OF
SELFIES WITH SERGEANT BUTLER. >> I KNOW THAT HE WAS ON OCEAN
AVENUE EVERY TIME I WAS THERE WHETHER I WAS THERE AS A
SUPERVISOR OR JUST BUYING GROCERIES AS A RESIDENT
AND OCCASIONALLY ON WEST PORTAL TWO YOU WERE EVERYWHERE AND YOU
EVERYBODY KNEW THE SCHEDULE OF OUR SHOPS AND YOU KNEW PEOPLE
AND YOU KNEW THE ELDERS THAT NEEDED SUPPORT.
YOU KNOW EVERYBODY AND EVERYBODY KNOWS YOU.
THAT IS TRULY THE BEST. WHAT SETS SERGEANT BUTLER APART
ASIDE FROM HIS SMILE IS THAT HE BELIEVES THAT EVERY INTERACTION
MATTERS. HE UNDERSTANDS THAT PUBLIC
SAFETY IS NOT ONLY ABOUT RESPONDING TO EMERGENCIES BUT
IT'S ALSO ABOUT BUILDING TRUST ,ABOUT STRENGTHENING
RELATIONSHIPS, ABOUT MAKING PEOPLE FEEL SEEN AND HEARD
INCLUDING ME AND VALUED. >> HIS APPROACH HAS EARNED HIM
THE ADMIRATION OF RESIDENTS, MERCHANTS, COLLEAGUES, EVERYONE
WHO KNOWS YOU AND HAS WORKED WITH YOU.
>> SERGEANT BUTLER'S COMMITMENT TO SERVICE HAS MADE A LASTING
IMPACT ON THE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT HE HAS SERVED.
HE HAS HELPED FOSTER STRONGER RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND COMMUNITY AND HIS LEADERSHIP HAS BEEN AN
EXAMPLE FOR OFFICERS THROUGHOUT THE DEPARTMENT.
THE RESIDENTS IN INGLESIDE AND TARAWA WILL DEFINITELY KNOW
YOU. YOU SHOW UP TO EVERY BARBECUE,
EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION PARTY.
>> YOU REALLY ARE EVERYWHERE, MY FRIEND.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE RESIDENTS OF DISTRICT SEVEN AND THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO, I EXTEND MY DEEPEST GRATITUDE TO
SERGEANT DREW KAI BUTLER FOR HIS YEARS OF DEDICATED SERVICE
TO TERRIBLE STATION IN OUR CITY.
WE THANK HIM FOR HIS COMMITMENT TO MAKING SAN FRANCISCO A
SAFER, MORE CONNECTED, MORE RESPECTFUL PLACE.
PLEASE JOIN ME AND CONGRATULATE READING SERGEANT DREW KAI
BUTLER IN WISHING HIM CONTINUED SUCCESS AT PARK STATION.
WORKING NIGHTS AND WE ARE JOINED TODAY BY TARA VAULT
CAPTAIN AND CAPTAIN HARMSEN. BUT BEFORE WE ASK CAPTAIN
HARBISON TO COME AND SAY A FEW WORDS AT SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES
WANT TO SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT YOU AS WELL.
>> OFFICER BUTLER AND THIS RESOLUTION IS IN THE QUEUE.
THANK YOU BOB PERSON. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAL GAR FOR OFFERING A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO
SERGEANT JEWEL KAI. THANK YOU.
I I YOU TRULY TRULY IS THE BEST OF THE BEST THAT I CAN THINK OF
AND I'M SO SO GRATEFUL FOR THE WORK THAT YOU ARE DOING AND YOU
HAVE BEEN DONE FOR OUR COMMUNITY AND FOR KEEPING OUR
COMMUNITY SAFE. >> I JUST WANT TO SHARE A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT, YOU KNOW, VERY PERSONAL EVEN BEFORE I I
AM ELECTED AS A SUPERVISOR THAT DURING COVID ON OCEAN AVENUE I
SEE YOU EVERY DAY THAT I GO SHOPPING THERE I SEE YOU AT THE
BAKERY. I SEE YOU AT THE LIBRARY.
>> I SEE YOU BASICALLY JUST EVERY CORNER OF OCEAN AVENUE I
YOU TRULY WITH YOUR SIGNATURE SMILE YOU KNOW YOU MAKE US FEEL
REALLY SAFE EVEN DURING THE TIME OF COVID.
I CAN'T THINK OF ANY OTHER PERSON REALLY EXEMPLIFY, YOU
KNOW, COMMUNITY POLICE THE WAY THAT YOU HAVE DEMONSTRATED.
THANK YOU FOR THAT. AND AND I ALSO WANT TO COMMEND
THAT YOUR KINDNESS, YOUR DILIGENCE AND YOUR WORK ETHIC
ALSO HAVE ALL THE MERCHANTS ON OCEAN AVENUE REALLY APPRECIATE
HAVING YOU. I NOW WALK OCEAN AVENUE PEOPLE
ASKING ME WHY ARE YOU HERE? >> WE MISS YOU AND AND I'M SURE
MANY TRY TO CALL YOU SO THIS IS LIKE YOU KNOW THE FEEDBACK THAT
I RECEIVE FROM CONSTITUENTS AND FROM MERCHANT REALLY
DEMONSTRATE WHO YOU ARE AND YOUR LEADERSHIP AND THE
IMPACT THAT YOU MAY IN OUR COMMUNITY.
THANK YOU AND I THANK YOU EVERYTHING FOR EVERYTHING THAT
YOU DO AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND CONGRATULATION
FOR YOUR PROMOTION. >> THANK YOU.
SO BEFORE WE LET YOU SPEAK, I THINK AT CAPTAIN HARBISON WAS
GOING TO SAY A FEW WORDS. WELCOME, CAPTAIN.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR IN MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD. >> THINGS NOT COOPERATING.
OKAY. IT'S REALLY AN HONOR TO BE HERE
TO CELEBRATE SERGEANT BUTLER. >> HE HAS BEEN AT TERRIBLE
STATION FOR EIGHT YEARS, SEVEN OF WHICH HAVE BEEN ON THE FOOTE
BEAT. AND I CAN TELL YOU THAT
SERGEANT BUTLER REALLY EMBODIES WHAT A BEAT OFFICER IS
AND SHOULD BE. I'M SURE SIR ROBERT PEEL IS
LOOKING DOWN AND REALLY AMAZED AT THE LEGACY THAT DUKE BUTLER
IS LIVING UP TO BECAUSE TRULY HE BELIEVES THAT THE POLICE ARE
THE COMMUNITY AND THE COMMUNITY ARE THE POLICE.
AND WITH EVERY INTERACTION HE HAS IT BLOWS ME AWAY JUST TO
SEE THE REACTION THAT HE GETS FROM THE COMMUNITY AND THE
AND THE GREAT ACCOMPLISHMENTS HE'S HAD IN TERRYVILLE AND ONCE
HE'S OFF PROBATION IF I CAN PULL SOME STRINGS I WILL TRY TO
GET HIM BACK TO THE TERRIBLE. >> I CONGRATULATE SERGEANT
BUTLER. >> I'M SERGEANT BUTLER.
I'M GETTING USED TO THE NEW TITLE.
I'M SO USED TO JUST BEING OFFICER BUTLER.
IT'S A PRIVILEGE AND AN HONOR TO STAND HERE BEFORE YOU ALL
TODAY. IT'S BEEN SUCH A JOY TO GET TO
MEET SO MANY OF YOU AND WORK WITH SO MANY OF YOU DISTRICT
FOUR, DISTRICT SEVEN, DISTRICT 11.
>> THE OPPORTUNITY TO GROW CLOSER AND WORK TOGETHER
AND PARTNER THAT I COULD BE A PART OF YOUR DIFFERENT
COMMUNITY EVENTS IN YOUR NEIGHBORHOOD MAKE A POSITIVE
IMPACT FOR YOU ALL WHO ARE HERE IN OUR CITY.
WELCOME TO MY FANTASTIC CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
WE HAVE THIS SPECTACULAR CITY. IT'S AN AWESOME PLACE TO HAVE
THE HONOR AND THE PRIVILEGE TO SERVE ALL OF YOU WHOEVER YOU
ARE IN OUR MAGNIFICENT CITY. SO IT IS WITH PRIDE AND JOY
THAT I TAKE THIS MOMENT TO JUST SAY THANK YOU TO YOU ALL.
LET'S REMEMBER THAT WE HAVE THIS SPECTACULAR GREAT CITY.
LET'S KEEP FIGHTING TO MAKE IT A GREAT CITY.
LET US BE KIND TO ONE ANOTHER. BE A NICE SMILE IN SOMEBODY'S
DAY. YOU MIGHT BE THAT ONLY SMILE
THAT MAKES A DIFFERENCE IN SOMEBODIES DAY.
THEY DON'T HAVE TO SMILE BACK. >> THEY DON'T HAVE TO SAY HI
BACK. BUT JUST GO OUT THERE AND MAKE
A POSITIVE DIFFERENCE AND IT'S SOMETHING THAT I'M JUST REALLY
PLEASED TO HAVE THE HONOR AND PRIVILEGE THAT I GET TO GO
OUT AND ESPECIALLY MY FOOT BIDETS AND JUST SAY HI TO
HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE EVERY WEEK AND JUST SHARE A SMILE AND IN
SOME CASES GET TO SHARE A HUG WITH SOMEBODY.
JUST TO LET THEM KNOW I'M HERE FOR YOU.
AND I PROUDLY REPRESENT SAN FRANCISCO AND I'M ANOTHER GREAT
PERSON IN THIS CITY AMONGST HUNDREDS OF OTHER OFFICERS WHO
GO OUT DAILY WITH THEIR HEART AS WELL AND LEAD THIS CITY
AND SERVE THIS CITY. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK
YOU, EVERYONE. AND I'M PROUD THAT I GET TO
CONTINUE SERVING THIS CITY. LOOK FORWARD TO WHAT IT MIGHT
BRING AND CAN'T WAIT TO SEE THE OTHER LIVES THAT WE GET TO
IMPACT AS A DEPARTMENT THAT WE GET TO IMPACT AS A CITY IN OUR
LITTLE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT WE HAVE HERE IN THIS SPECTACULAR
SPECTACULAR CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
SO I'M VERY PROUD TO REPRESENT JUST ONE MEMBER OF OUR
DEPARTMENT OUT OF HUNDREDS WHO DO THIS FANTASTIC JOB ALL THE
TIME. THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
AND HAVE A WONDERFUL REST OF YOUR DAY
. >> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON THANK YOU SO MUCH, MR. PRESIDENT.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY WE ARE HERE TO HONOR AND CELEBRATE AN
EXTRAORDINARY PUBLIC SERVANT DIRECTOR SHEREEN MCSPADDEN WITH
THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING.
>> IT IS MY DISTINCT PRIVILEGE TO RECOGNIZE SHEREEN IN HONOR
OF HER RETIREMENT AND TO THANK HER FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES
OF DEDICATED SERVICE TO SENIORS PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES
AND INDIVIDUALS AND FAMILIES EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS.
AS A PROUD BAYVIEW RESIDENT AND DISTRICT TANK CONSTITUENT,
SERENA'S COMMITMENT TO PUBLIC SERVICE HAS EXTENDED FAR BEYOND
HER PROFESSIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES.
SHE HAS NOT ONLY WORKED ON BEHALF OF SAN FRANCISCANS
THROUGHOUT HER CAREER BUT HAS ALSO BEEN AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF
THE COMMUNITY. SHE CALLS HOME.
WHEN SHEREEN WAS APPOINTED EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IN 2021,
SHE STEPPED INTO ONE OF THE MOST CHALLENGING LEADERSHIP
ROLES IN LOCAL GOVERNMENT. SHE BROUGHT WITH HER A DEEP
UNDERSTANDING OF PUBLIC SERVICE, A COMMITMENT TO EQUITY
AND A VISION FOR BUILDING SYSTEMS THAT TRULY SERVE PEOPLE
WITH DIGNITY AND RESPECT. OVER THE COURSE OF HER TENURE,
SHEREEN TRANSFORMED NOT ONLY A DEPARTMENT BUT THE WAY SAN
FRANCISCO APPROACHES HOMELESSNESS.
SHE STRENGTHENED ACCOUNTABILITY THROUGH DATA DRIVEN PLANNING
AND PERFORMANCE MANAGEMENT. >> ESTABLISHED THE DEPARTMENT'S
FIRST EQUITY OFFICE AND EMBEDDED RACIAL EQUITY INTO
THE FABRIC OF THIS WORK. HER LEADERSHIP ENSURED THAT THE
VOICES OF PEOPLE WITH LIVED EXPERIENCE HELPED SHAPE POLICY
AND PRACTICE CREATING A MORE RESPONSIVE AND INCLUSIVE SYSTEM
. UNDER HER GUIDANCE AGENCY
EXPANDED SHELTER CAPACITY LAUNCHED INNOVATIVE PROGRAMS
SUCH AS THE CITY'S FIRST CABIN COMMUNITIES.
THE FIRST SHELTER SPECIFICALLY DESIGNED FOR OLDER ADULTS
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS AND ADVANCED RECOVERY FOCUSED
SERVICES THAT HAVE HELPED HUNDREDS OF INDIVIDUALS BEGIN
NEW CHAPTERS IN THEIR LIVES. DURING HER LEADERSHIP,
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE MOVED FROM HOMELESSNESS INTO STABLE
HOUSING. THOUSANDS MORE HOUSEHOLDS WERE
PREVENTED FROM BECOMING HOMELESS.
AND TENS OF THOUSANDS OF ADULTS, FAMILIES AND CHILDREN
RECEIVED CRITICAL SHELTER AND SUPPORT SERVICES.
>> SERENE ALSO UNDERSTOOD THAT LASTING CHANGE REQUIRES
PARTNERSHIP. SHE STRENGTHENED COLLABORATION,
COLLABORATE MISSION ACROSS CITY DEPARTMENTS COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATIONS, ADVOCATES, PHILANTHROPY, NEIGHBORHOOD
STAKEHOLDERS AND SERVICE PROVIDERS HELPING BUILD A MORE
COORDINATED AND EFFECTIVE RESPONSE TO HOMELESSNESS
THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO. HER LEADERSHIP HAS LEFT A
LASTING IMPACT ON OUR CITY. OUR INSTITUTIONS AND THE
COUNTLESS LIVES SHE HAS TOUCHED ALONG THE WAY WE EXTEND OUR
DEEPEST GRATITUDE FOR YOUR YEARS OF SERVICE AND VISIONARY
LEADERSHIP. YOUR LEGACY WILL CONTINUE TO
SHAPE THIS CITY FOR YEARS TO COME.
WE CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR WILL EARN RETIREMENT AND WISH
YOU HAPPINESS, FULFILLMENT, JOY AND ALL YOU DESERVE.
AND THE CHAPTER HEAD I WANT YOU TO JOIN ME IN CELEBRATING
AND HONORING SHEREEN FOR HER REMARKABLE CAREER AND ENDURING
CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
AND THANK YOU FOR TAKING ON ONE OF THE HARDEST TASK IN PUBLIC
SERVICE AND RUNNING THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS.
AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING DURING A CRUCIAL AND PIVOTAL TIME THAT
SAYS A LOT ABOUT YOUR CHARACTER .
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. AND AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK, I
HAVE SOME COLLEAGUES THAT WANT TO SAY SOME NICE WORDS AND THEN
WE ALSO WANT TO BRING UP CHIEF KUNAL MODI TO SAY SOMETHING AS
WELL. >> AND WE WILL START WITH
SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> THANK YOU.
AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR HONORING FOR AMOS BAD AND I
AM CERTAINLY GRATEFUL FOR YOUR WORK AND YOUR LEADERSHIP.
I DO AGREE IT'S THE SOME OF THE TOUGHEST TIME THAT THE CITY HAS
EVER FACED BE IT THE THE PANDEMIC RECOVERY AND AND JUST
SEEING SO MANY HOMELESS INDIVIDUALS ON OUR STREETS,
PARTICULARLY THOSE WHO ARE SENIORS THAT YOU HAVE BROUGHT A
LOT OF UNDERSTANDING AND CONTEXT ABOUT HOW WE AS A
CITY CAN BEST SERVE THEM AND SUPPORT THEM.
>> BUT I WANT TO EXPRESS MY DEEPEST GRATITUDE TO YOU ON THE
MOST PERSONAL LEVEL THAT NOT ONLY FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP BUT
ALSO FOR YOUR KNOWLEDGE AND COMPASSION, PARTICULARLY
YOUR COMPASSION AND YOUR CHARACTER.
ABSOLUTELY CONCUR WITH A SUPERVISOR AT WALTON AND JUST
MENTIONING YOUR CHARACTER AND YOUR INTEGRITY AND WHO YOU
ARE. DURING OUR WORK TOGETHER I
THINK REALLY THE LAST YEAR FOR A LOT OF HOMELESS FAMILIES.
AND BE IT THOSE WHO ARE UNDOCUMENTED OR THOSE WHO ARE
JUST NEWLY ARRIVED AND THE IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY AND AND
THOSE FAMILIES WITH KIDS WHO ARE SICK AND ON SO MANY LEVEL
AND JUST SEEING HOW YOU AND YOUR TEAM WORK TOGETHER
AND MAKING SURE AND PRIORITIZING RESOURCES FOR
THEM IN A WAY THAT ALSO STILL NOT LEAVING SO MANY OTHER
PEOPLE BEHIND. IT'S A VERY, VERY DIFFICULT
TASK AND BECAUSE AS WE HAVE TALKED ABOUT THE RESOURCES IS
NEVER GOING TO BE ENOUGH FOR FOR EVERY FAMILY THAT YOU PLACE
. IT'S JUST DEMORALIZING WATCHING
YOU DOING THE WORK BECAUSE FOR EVERY FAMILIES THAT YOU PLACE
FOR PERMANENT HOME TO THREE, FOUR AND MORE FAMILIES BECAME
HOMELESS DURING THE VERY SAME PERIOD OF TIME.
YET YOU KEPT AT IT YOU NEVER GAVE UP AND YOU ALWAYS ALWAYS
DID IT WITH SUCH A CALM DEMEANOR AND AND IN SUCH A
PROBLEM SOLVING MODE IS WHAT I HAVE.
I JUST RESPECT YOU THE MOST FOR THAT AND I AM VERY GRATEFUL
AND THANK YOU FOR THE WORK THAT YOU HAVE DONE.
ALONG WITH MY WORK AS BUDGET COMMITTEE CHAIR YOU MADE THAT
WORK NOT ONLY GOOD BUT ACTUALLY VERY MEANINGFUL.
YOU HELP US UNDERSTAND THE IMPACT AND THE COMMITMENT THAT
THE CITY MUST MAKE FOR EVERY DOLLAR TO MAKE SURE IT COUNTS.
I AGREE WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON THAT THOUSANDS, TENS
AND THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE ARE MUCH BETTER OFF TODAY BECAUSE
OF WHO YOU ARE AND YOUR LEADERSHIP AND YOUR COMPASSION
AND SO YOU SHOULD BE VERY PROUD, SO PROUD THE WORK THAT
YOU HAVE DONE YOU HAVE DONE IT NOT ONLY IN THE BEST INTERESTS
OF SAN FRANCISCAN, YOU HAVE DONE IT IN THE BEST INTERESTS
OF HUMANITY. SO FOR THAT I AM VERY, VERY
GRATEFUL AND I THINK THAT REALLY FOR THE MOST VULNERABLE
FAMILIES IN SAN FRANCISCO ON BEHALF OF THEM THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR WORK. >> THANK YOU.
CHURCH AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR SO SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU SO
MUCH. AND SO I FIRST WANT TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THE GREAT WORK YOU HAVE DONE FOR THIS CITY BEFORE
THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS WHEN YOU WORKED AT DISABILITY
AGING SERVICES AND INSTITUTED THE FIRST BATCH OF PLANS FOR
THE SERVICES TO THIS POPULATION THAT THE DEPARTMENT PRODUCED.
YOU HAVE ALWAYS BEEN SO STRATEGIC AND COMPETENT BUT
ALSO DOING IT WITH GREAT HEART AND EMPATHY.
SO I WORKED WITH YOU VERY CLOSELY WHEN WE TACKLED THE
GROWTH OF THE POPULATION OF FOLKS LIVING IN VEHICLES
IN DISTRICT SEVEN. I PROBABLY CAN'T DO TOO MUCH
FOR YOUR COMFORT. >> I'M SO SORRY BUT THAT'S
BECAUSE I TRUSTED YOU. YOU KNOW, DESPITE ALL OF THE
CHALLENGES, THE IMPEDIMENTS PEOPLE SAY WHATEVER THEY WANT.
>> I WANTED TO HEAR YOU. YOU WERE ALWAYS HONEST
AND STRAIGHT UP AND TRANSPARENT BUT ALSO DELIVER URGENT IN YOUR
LEADERSHIP OF YOUR STAFF TO DELIVER THE THINGS THAT WE
NEEDED TO GET TO. SO SHEREEN, I'M REALLY SORRY
THAT YOU'RE LEAVING. >> I AM I'M GLAD FOR YOUR WIFE
THAT YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE A LITTLE MORE TIME AND I THINK
WE'RE GOING TO REALLY MISS YOUR WISDOM, YOUR INTELLIGENCE, YOUR
STRATEGY BUT I KNOW THAT YOU ARE GOING TO GO ON TO YOUR LIFE
OUTSIDE OF THE CITY AND COUNTY SAN FRANCISCO.
BUT THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE FOR THE
CITY. THANK YOU FOR WHAT YOU'VE DONE
FOR OUR MOST VULNERABLE RESIDENTS TO GIVE PEOPLE A
CHANCE AT A BETTER LIFE A LIFE AFTER RECOVERY, A LIFE AFTER
HAVING BEEN AT THE BOTTOM ONE THAT HAS SUCCESS.
YOU KNOW IN FRONT YOU HAVE DONE ALL THAT.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
SHEREEN I HAVE HAD RESPECT AND AFFECTION FOR YOU LONG
BEFORE WE ACTUALLY HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK TOGETHER
IN THIS BUILDING BUT BACK IN 2019 WHEN YOU WERE OUT ON
THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL AND I WAS I THINK WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON
WORKING AGAINST JEWEL LABS AND ANOTHER BALLOT MEASURE
AND JUST YOU KNOW, SEEING YOU OUT THERE AND OF COURSE AS A
RUNNING PARTNER AND THINGS I REALLY RESPECT HOW YOU HAVE
STEPPED UP AND SERVED THE CITY IN SOME REALLY DIFFICULT ROLES
AND DIFFICULT TIMES. AND AS I SAID, I THINK I THINK
THIS WAS THE QUOTE THAT I GAVE TO THE B.A.R.
THAT I WOULD CONGRATULATE YOU ON YOUR RETIREMENT BUT I
ANTICIPATE THAT I WILL BE INTERRUPTING IT WITH CALLS FOR
ADVICE EARLY AND OFTEN TOO JUST BECAUSE YOU JUST HAVE SO MUCH
KNOWLEDGE THAT I REALLY APPRECIATE EVERYTHING THAT YOU
HAVE DONE SO I HOPE YOU DON'T MIND I MAY BE INTERRUPTING YOUR
RETIREMENT FROM TIME TO TIME. >> THANKS.
SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU FOR PRESIDENT FOR
SURE. AND I EVEN ONLY WANT YOU KNOW,
JUST A LITTLE OVER A YEAR AND INSIDE THIS CHAMBER AND AND
TO WHAT YOU HAVE DEMONSTRATED AND THE PARTNERSHIP THE
COLLABORATION AND YOUR LEADERSHIP YOUR COMPASSION TO
THIS HOMELESSNESS ISSUES IN OUR CITY, THIS IS A VERY COMPLEX
ISSUES WE ALL UNDERSTAND. BUT I JUST WANT TO HIGHLIGHT,
YOU KNOW, THE LITTLE TIME THAT WE WORKED TOGETHER YOUR YOUR
DETAILS AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO SOLVING AND GETTING DATA
AND GETTING TO UNDERSTAND EVERY SINGLE CASE.
AND I REMEMBER OUR CONVERSATION ABOUT SOLVING OUR FAMILY
HOMELESSNESS THAT YOU ARE ABLE TO REALLY TRACK DOWN EVERY
SINGLE FAMILY AND THEIR STATUS AND TRYING TO SUPPORT EVERY
SINGLE ONE OF THEM. AND WITH THAT WHAT ETHIC
AND PROFESSIONAL AND LOVE AND IT SPEAKS A LOT ABOUT YOU
KNOW WHO YOU ARE AND YOU WILL BE MISSED AND I BUT I ALSO
AGAIN I REALLY APPRECIATE ALL THAT YOU HAVE DONE FOR THE CITY
AND FOR SOLVING THIS CRISIS FOR THE CITY AND I WISH YOU A HAPPY
RELAXING RETIREMENT. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU
DIRECTOR, FOR ALL YOUR WORK. I JUST WANT TO COMMENT ON TWO
FACETS ONE AND WORKING OVER THE LAST YEAR TOGETHER JUST THE
INCREDIBLE AMOUNT OF COLLABORATION YOUR DEPARTMENT
AND TEAM HAVE HAD AND I STEMS FROM THE TOP DOWN.
WE WORKED ON SOME HARD LEGISLATION TOGETHER WITH THE
GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY ORDINANCE BUT IT WAS THROUGH THAT
COLLABORATION THAT WE CAME OUT WITH A STRONGER PIECE OF
LEGISLATION THAN WHEN WE STARTED AND HAVE A LOT OF YOU
AND YOUR TEAM TO THANK FOR THAT.
AND AS A RESULT OF THAT WE HAVE LIKE MORE DATA ABOUT THINGS
THAT ARE HAPPENING AND I THINK SECOND ALSO JUST IT'S BEEN
GREAT TO GO TO DIFFERENT SITES POTENTIALLY SITES THAT WILL
HOPEFULLY BE ANNOUNCING SOON AND DISTRICT FIVE AND THE HEART
AND HUMANITY AND EMPATHY THAT YOU HAVE FOR ADDRESSING THIS
CRISIS. YOU'VE MADE A PERMANENT IMPACT
ON THE CULTURE OF THE DEPARTMENT.
SO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR SERVICE.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHARI AND I JUST WANT TO SAY WHAT A
PLEASURE IT'S BEEN ABLE TO BE TO WORK WITH YOU OVER THE LAST
FOUR YEARS YOUR WILLINGNESS TO EMBRACE NEW IDEAS AND NEW
STRATEGIES IN THE FACE OF OMNIPRESENT CHALLENGES I THINK
IS VERY UNIQUE, IS VERY DIFFICULT AND I JUST WANT TO
THANK YOU FOR BRINGING THAT EACH AND EVERY DAY.
>> WE WILL MISS YOU. THANK YOU.
I HAVE A COUPLE OF THOUGHTS. ONE IS I LIKE SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. I DO WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THE
WORK THAT YOU DID BEFORE H.S. BECAUSE I HEARD WHEN I FIRST
GOT TO KNOW YOU IT WAS BECAUSE YOU WERE SORT OF THE ZERO WHO
HAD IMPLEMENTED MANY OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS AROUND LGBTQ
AGING IN SAN FRANCISCO AND YOU WERE BEING CELEBRATED BY PEOPLE
LIKE MARCY ADELMAN, TOM NOLAN WHO I THINK WORKED FOR YOU
MAYBE THEN THAT COULD BE. >> BUT A LOT OF FOLKS WHO'D
DONE A LOT OF GOOD WORK TO TRY AND ADDRESS SOME OF THE NEEDS
OF AGING LGBT SENIORS AND YOU HAD BEEN GREAT AROUND THAT
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR TOUR OF DUTY HERE.
>> LIKE IT HAS BEEN I WOULD IMAGINE AN INCREDIBLY ROUGH
TIME AND YET YOU'VE DONE AMAZING WORK.
I THINK ONE OF THE CHALLENGES FOR LEADERS PUBLIC SECTOR
LEADERS IN SAN FRANCISCO IS YOU'RE NOT ONLY TRYING TO DO
THE WORK, YOU'RE ALSO LIKE MANAGING POLITICAL HEADWINDS,
GOING IN ALL THESE DIFFERENT DIRECTIONS AND I THINK THERE'S
PROBABLY NO ONE IN THE CITY NO LEADER OF A DEPARTMENT THAT HAS
BEEN MORE IN THE SPOTLIGHT AND MORE SUBJECT TO BEING
PUSHED IN A MILLION DIFFERENT DIRECTIONS BY ME AND EACH OF MY
COLLEAGUES. WE ALL THINK WE HAVE THE
SOLUTIONS. WE DO NOT AGREE WITH EACH OTHER
. WE DON'T NECESSARILY AGREE WITH
THE MAYOR. WE DON'T NECESSARILY AGREE WITH
THE NUMBERS OF HOMELESSNESS OVERSIGHT COMMISSION OR THE
VARIOUS MYRIAD OTHER BODIES TO WHICH YOU ANSWER AND IT'S JUST
AND THEN YOU HAVE THIS VAST CONSTITUENCY OF OUR NONPROFIT
PARTNERS AND AND EVERYONE AND IT'S NOT JUST ALL OF US WHO
HAVE OPINIONS LIKE THE WHOLE CITY HAS OPINIONS AND EVERYONE
IS GIVING THEM TO YOU. SO IN ALL OF THAT CACOPHONY
AND CHAOS AND DEMAND YOU HAVE BEEN EXTRAORDINARY AND SO THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR HONORING AN EXTRAORDINARY
PUBLIC SERVANT AND THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU STREAM MCSPADDEN
FOR YOUR EXCELLENT PUBLIC SERVICE AND I BELIEVE
SUPERVISOR WALTON WE WERE YOU WANTED TO GIVE CHIEF MOTY A
MOMENT AS WELL. SHEREEN EVERY DAY I WORK
IN THIS BUILDING I'M FILLED WITH MORE AND MORE HUMILITY
BECAUSE THIS PUBLIC SERVICE IS REALLY HARD AND MAKING CHANGE
IS REALLY HARD AND YOU'VE BEEN DOING IT FOR 23 YEARS AND AS
EVERYONE HAS SAID YOU'VE DONE IT WITH INTEGRITY, YOU'VE DONE
IT WITH GRACE AND YOU'VE DONE IT WITH COMPASSION ON SOME OF
OUR CITY'S TOUGHEST CHALLENGES HELPING OLDER ADULTS AGE WITH
DIGNITY, FIGHTING FOR DISABILITY JUSTICE AND MAKING
OUR CITY MORE INCLUSIVE, HELPING PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS FIND STABILITY. I SHARE THIS STORY AT
COMMISSION LAST WEEK BUT IT BEARS REPEATING I WAS REALLY
MOVED WHEN WE VISITED THE GROUNDBREAKING OF THE KELSEY
TOGETHER WITH SOME OF THE SUPERVISORS HERE.
IT'S THE FIRST MUNICIPALLY FUNDED AFFORDABLE HOUSING
COMPLEX FOR FOLKS WITH DISABILITIES THAT'S DESIGNED
FROM THE GROUND UP WITH UNIVERSAL ACCESSIBLE DESIGN
PRINCIPLES. IT WAS SOMETHING CONCEIVED
DURING YOUR LEADERSHIP AT DOS AND THAT WAS FINISHED
AND OPENED AFTER YOU HAD LEFT THE DEPARTMENT AND IT MADE ME
THINK ABOUT HOW MANY THINGS THAT WE'LL CELEBRATE IN THIS
BUILDING YEARS FROM NOW THAT HAVE YOUR FINGER PRINTS
AND EARLY IDEAS HAVING SHAPED THEM.
AND SO WE'RE GOING TO BE THE BENEFICIARIES OF YOUR SERVICE
FOR YEARS TO COME THAT HSA THAT YOU TOOK ON UNDOUBTEDLY ONE OF
THE TOUGHEST, TOUGHEST ASSIGNMENTS THE CITY HAS TO
OFFER AND YOU REALLY STABILIZED THE DEPARTMENT.
YOU BUILT SYSTEMS, YOU BUILT A TEAM WHICH CONTINUES TO BE PART
OF YOUR LEGACY AND I KNOW WILL COLLECTIVELY ALL TRY
AND CONTINUE TO MAKE YOU PROUD AND YOU'VE DELIVERED SO MANY
RESULTS FOR PEOPLE THROUGH ONE OF THE TOUGHEST TIMES THIS CITY
HAS SEEN THROUGH THE PANDEMIC AND SO I JUST WANT TO SAY YOU
HAVE A BIG HEART. YOU HAVE A BIG BRAIN AND ARE SO
OUR CITY IS SO LUCKY THAT YOU PUT THEM IN SERVICE TO IT.
AND SO ON BEHALF OF THE MAYOR, AS A COLLEAGUE AND AS A
RESIDENT, I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE.
SHEREEN MCSPADDEN THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> WAIT, ARE YOU SURE YOU WANT TO GIVE ME THE FLOOR?
SO I JUST WANT TO START OFF BY THANKING SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR
THIS FOR THIS AFTERNOON. IT'S REALLY SPECIAL TO ME.
I AND THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
I WANT TO SAY THAT IT HAS REALLY BEEN AN HONOR TO WORK
WITH EACH ONE OF YOU AND I'VE GOTTEN TO WORK WITH MOST OF YOU
VERY CLOSELY OVER THE YEARS. I ALSO JUST WANT TO SAY IF YOU
JUST HAD AGREED WITH ME THINGS WOULD HAVE BEEN A LOT EASIER
FOR ALL OF US. NO, BUT I MEAN I KNOW WE WERE
OFTEN NOT I'VE NOT EVEN OFTEN BUT SOMETIMES ON OPPOSITE SIDES
OF ARGUMENTS AND THINGS LIKE THAT.
AND I JUST HAVE TO SAY THAT I KNOW VERY WELL THAT ALL OF US
ARE INCREDIBLY DEDICATED TO THIS WONDERFUL CITY THAT WE
LIVE IN AND THAT'S WHERE THAT ALL COMES FROM AND IT'S BEEN IT
REALLY HAS BEEN A PLEASURE TO WORK WITH ALL OF YOU, REALLY
APPRECIATE THAT. I ALSO WANT TO THANK KUNAL.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WHAT YOU SAID TOO AND I REALLY THINK
THAT THE CITY IS IN VERY GOOD HANDS.
I'M EXCITED ABOUT A LOT OF THE DIRECTION THAT WE'RE GOING
IN PARTICULARLY AS WE THINK ABOUT DEPARTMENTS COLLABORATING
SO WELL TOGETHER AND YOU KNOW WE'VE REALLY NEEDED THAT RESET
AND I THINK THAT'S GOING TO BE REALLY HELPFUL FOR PEOPLE WHO
NEED OUR SERVICES MOST IF WE CAN BE ALIGNED ACROSS
DEPARTMENTS AND AS A CITY TOGETHER WE'RE GOING TO DO
BETTER BY PEOPLE WHO LIVE HERE. I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES.
SOME OF THEM ARE HERE TODAY AND YOU KNOW, IT TURNS OUT THAT
ACTUALLY SOLVING HOMELESSNESS AND MAKING THINGS EASIER FOR
OLDER PEOPLE IN A VERY HILLY CITY FULL OF STAIRS I MEAN NONE
OF THESE THINGS ARE EASY AND THEY KNOW BECAUSE THEY DO
THIS EVERY DAY. EVERY DAY MY STAFF IS SOLVING
HOMELESSNESS FOR SOMEONE EVERY DAY.
WHEN I WORKED AT THE DEPARTMENT OF AGING PEOPLE WERE DOING
THINGS TO MAKE SOME OLDER PERSON'S LIFE BETTER.
AND SO YOU KNOW, I'M REALLY, REALLY GRATEFUL TO ALL OF THEM.
IT'S BEEN A PLEASURE TO BE THEIR COLLEAGUE AS SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD SAID, YOU KNOW, WE HAVE A REALLY GOOD TEAM.
WE WORK WELL TOGETHER AND I'M JUST GRATEFUL TO THEM AND I'M
REALLY GRATEFUL FOR ALL OF THE FOLKS WHO PROVIDE SERVICES
IN OUR COMMUNITY, PARTICULARLY THE PEOPLE WHO'VE DONE THE
HOMEWORK TO UNDERSTAND WHAT SPECIFIC COMMUNITIES NEED.
I MEAN WE HAVE SO MANY GREAT ORGANIZATIONS THAT ARE BIG
AND SMALL THAT SERVE BLACK AND BROWN PEOPLE THAT SERVE
WOMEN REALLY WELL OLDER ADULTS, FAMILIES AND YOUTH.
AND I THINK WE'RE JUST I MEAN SOMETIMES WE WORRY ABOUT HAVING
TOO MANY AND MAYBE THAT'S THE CASE BUT WE ALSO HAVE A HUGE
AMOUNT OF EXPERTISE IN THIS CITY AND WE'RE FORTUNATE FOR
THAT. YOU KNOW, I ALSO REALLY WANT TO
THANK PEOPLE WHO COME FORWARD TO TELL US WHAT THEY NEED
BECAUSE IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT TO DO THIS WORK BY HEARING FROM
PEOPLE WHO ARE EXPERIENCING THE THINGS THAT WE'RE TRYING TO
SOLVE. RIGHT.
AND SO I WANT TO THANK PEOPLE I KNOW THERE ARE MANY PEOPLE
IN THIS ROOM WHO'VE EXPERIENCED HOMELESSNESS WHO ARE AGING
IN OUR CITY JUST REALLY WANT TO THANK THEM FOR COMING FORTH
AND BEING BRAVE AND SHARING THEIR OPPORTUNITIES.
IT'S BEEN A REAL PLEASURE TO WORK WITH EVERYONE HERE ON ALL
OF THESE PROBLEMS AND I KNOW THAT ALL OF YOU WILL CONTINUE
THAT WORK AND I WANT TO THANK MY WIFE JAY WHO'S HERE FOR ALL
OF THE SUPPORT. >> I MEAN IT'S I THINK IT'S
REALLY HARD TO BE THE SPOUSE OF SOMEONE WHO WORKS IN FIELDS
LIKE THIS AND I PROBABLY BRING A LOT OF THE ANGST HOME AND SO
I JUST REALLY WANT TO THANK HER FOR HER UNWAVERING SUPPORT
THROUGHOUT THAT MY THROUGHOUT MY ENTIRE CAREER WITH THE CITY
SO THANK YOU'D J AND I THINK THAT'S IT THAT'S ALL I HAVE TO
SAY THANK YOU SURPRISED ONE SPRING DIRECTOR MCSPADDEN THE
WELL I'M SORRY MAN I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT THAT'S YOUR NATURAL
HAIR COLOR
DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR JEN THANK YOU BOB PERCENT.
PLEASE JOIN ME IN WELCOMING JEFFERSON JOHNSON TO THE PODIUM
. >> COLLEAGUES, I'M VERY PROUD
TO RECOGNIZE A YEAR WHO IS PERSISTENT, HUMBLE AND DEEPLY
ROOTED IN HIS COMMUNITY. JEFFERSON JOHNSON WAS BORN
IN ANDORRA AND IMMIGRATED TO THE UNITED STATE WHEN HE WAS 16
YEARS OLD. HE ATTENDED MISSION HIGH SCHOOL
AND JOINED HAUMEA IN 2023 BY HIS PEERS AND PROGRAM
COORDINATORS. JEFFERSON IS DESCRIBED AS A
YOUNG MAN WHO DOES NOT GIVE UP AND IS KNOWN FOR HIS CARE
AND LOVE FOR HIS FRIENDS AND PEERS.
>> ON APRIL 9TH, 2026, A FELLOW PROGRAM PARTICIPANT WHO WAS
SHOT NEXT TO DOOR NEXT DOOR WHILE GETTING LUNCH, JEFFERSON
APPLIED IT LIFE SAVING FIRST EXCUSE THAT HE LEARNED FROM
IN LANGUAGE TRAINING A FEW WEEKS PRIOR AND STABILIZED AT
HIS FRIEND LONG ENOUGH FOR THE PARAMEDICS TO ARRIVE ON THE
SCENE TO AID JEFFERSON APPLY. >> HE QUICKLY THINKING AND HE'S
BRAVELY MADE THE CRITICAL DIFFERENCE IN SAVING A YOUNG
LIFE THAT DAY. I ALSO WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT TO
EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE FOR HOMIE .
HOMIE HAS BEEN TRANSFORMING THE LIVES OF AT RISK YOUTH
IN DISTRICT NINE, TEN AND 11. THROUGH A LEADERSHIP SKILLS
DEVELOPMENT AND MENTORSHIP GROUP BREATHING LIFE
EMPOWERMENT AND COMMUNITY INVOLVE HIM IN THEIR
PARTICIPANTS. THE SITUATION HIGHLIGHTS THE
IMPORTANCE OF OUR SOCIAL SAFETY NET AND THE COMMUNITY SERVICES
AND THE COMMUNITY SERVING ORGANIZATIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO
WHERE COMMUNITY MEMBERS CAN ACCESS LIFE SAVING TRAINING
IN LANGUAGE ACCESSIBLE TO THEM AS WELL.
TODAY I WANT TO TAKE THE OPPORTUNITY TO HONOR AND THANK
JEFFERSON FOR APPLYING THIS VALUABLE SKILLS.
THANK YOU JEFFERSON FOR EMBODYING THE VALUE OF
PERSISTENCE AND RELIANCE. AND THANK YOU FOR STEPPING UP
AND SAVING THE LIFE OF A FELLOW PROGRAM PARTICIPANT.
>> THANK YOU. >> WHEN I STARTED THE
ENVIRONMENTAL WORK I SAW HOW THE US YEAH IMPLEMENT LUGARD
GET ORGANIZED, HOW THE US AND SAY I WANT THEM IN MY
POCKET. I SAID HEY YEAH SO YOU KNOW
AND WE KORERO
HUH? >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
SURPRISE I'M GOING TO JUST TRANSLATE OR DO MY BEST TO
TRANSLATE. HE KIND OF WENT OFF SCRIPT SO
I'M GOING TO DO THE READ THE SCRIPT AND THEN SHOOT.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS JEFFERSON JOHNSON.
FIRST I GIVE THANKS TO GOD AND SECOND TO MY MOM BECAUSE
THANKS TO HER I AM STRONG PERSON AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR THIS RECOGNITION.
WHEN I WAS YOUNG THE STREETS TAUGHT ME MANY THINGS JUST AS
THEY TAUGHT ME THE BAD THEY ALSO TAUGHT ME THE GOOD.
I LEARNED TO BECOME STRONGER AND NEVER GIVE UP.
I FEEL THAT THE ONLY THING THAT WE NEED IS LOVE.
THE WORK WON'T CHANGE UNLESS WE SHOW LOVE TO OUR NEIGHBORS WHAT
HELPS ME CHANGE IS EVERYONE GUIDING ME HAS TAUGHT ME THE
CONCEPT OF YOU ARE THE OTHER VERSION OF ME.
THIS MEANS WE ARE ALL CONNECTED AND YES IF I HURT YOU I HURT
MYSELF, I'VE HURT MYSELF, I HURT YOU.
I AM GRATEFUL FOR THE PEOPLE GOD HAS PLACED IN MY PATH.
THEY HAVE BECOME A SECOND FAMILY TO ME AND THEY HAVE
TURNED ME INTO A WARRIOR AND A ROLE MODEL FOR MY ENTIRE
COMMUNITY. MY MESSAGE TO ALL THE YOUTH IS
LET'S FOLLOW OUR DREAMS AND NO MATTER HOW HARD THINGS GET, LET
US NOT FORGET THAT WE ARE THE PRESENT FOR A BETTER FUTURE.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. HE ALSO SAID THAT'S NOT IN HERE
BUT HE ALSO SAID HE WANTED TO THANK CAL POLY AND ALL THE
PEOPLE HERE THAT HAVE HELPED THEM DEVELOP.
AND I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE EBBY BECAUSE IVY WAS ALSO THERE
THE THE DAY THAT THAT YOUNG MAN WAS CAME INTO OUR OFFICE
BLEEDING OUT. THEY BOTH QUICKLY JUST WENT
INTO ACTION AND SAVED THE YOUNG PERSON'S LIFE AND I THINK IT'S
WHERE I'M EXTREMELY PROUD OF THESE TWO YOUNG INDIVIDUALS FOR
THE LIFESAVING WORK THAT THEY'VE DONE.
>> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH EVERYBODY
. >> ALL RIGHT.
CAN I INVITE UP DIKES ON BIKES? >> PRESIDENT KATE BROWN AND AS
MANY OF HER DIKES ON BIKES AS SHE WOULD LIKE TO BRING WITH
HER OR 50 YEARS THE UNMISTAKABLE ROAR OF DIKES ON
BIKES, MOTORCYCLES HAS SIGNALED THE START OF PRIDE PRIDE
PARADES NOT JUST IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT AROUND THE WORLD
PARIS, LONDON, TOKYO, MELBOURNE AND BEYOND WHAT IS NOW AN
INTERNATIONAL PRIDE TRADITION BEGAN RIGHT HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WHEN ABOUT 2025 FEMALE MOTORCYCLISTS DECIDED TO
RIDE THEIR BIKES IN THE 1976 SAN FRANCISCO GAY FREEDOM DAY
PARADE NOT WANTING TO STORE THEIR BIKES BEHIND OTHER SLOWER
MOVING CONTINGENTS THE GROUP BOLDLY CLAIMED A POSITION AT
THE VERY FRONT OF THE PARADE AND DIKES ON BIKES HAVE PROUDLY
LED EVERY PARADE SINCE. ALTHOUGH THEY ARE BEST KNOWN
FOR THEIR COMMANDING PRESENCE IN PRIDE PARADES, DIKES ON
BIKES HAS ALSO WON A MAJOR VICTORY FOR FREE EXPRESSION
AND LGBTQ PLUS RIGHTS IN A LANDMARK SUPREME COURT CASE
THAT UPHELD THEIR RIGHT TO CLAIM AND TRADEMARK THEIR NAME
FIRST COINED BY A MEMBER DURING THE 1976 PARADE.
THE NAME DIKES ON BIKES WAS ADOPTED AS THE GROUP'S OFFICIAL
NAME AFTER IT WAS PRINTED IN THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE
IN 2003. THE ORGANIZATION APPLIED TO
TRADEMARK THEIR NAME BUT THE UNITED STATES PATENT
AND TRADEMARK OFFICE WHICH I WILL REFER TO AS THE USPTO
REJECTED THE APPLICATION CLAIMING THE TERM WAS
DEROGATORY. DIKES ON BIKES SUBMITTED
MOUNTAINS OF EVIDENCE FROM HISTORIANS, CARTOONISTS
SCHOLARS SHOWING THAT THE LESBIAN COMMUNITY CONSIDERED
THE TERM SELF-REFERENCE RACIAL RATHER THAN DEROGATORY.
>> ALTHOUGH THE USPTO EVENTUALLY GRANTED THE
TRADEMARK IN 2006 A MAN SUED THE GROUP A YEAR LATER CLAIMING
THE NAME WAS SCANDALOUS, IMMORAL, DISPARAGING TO MEN.
>> DIKES ON BIKES CONTINUED FIGHTING TO TRADEMARK THEIR
NAME AND LOGO UNTIL 2017 WHEN THE SUPREME COURT RULED
UNANIMOUS SLATE THAT DENYING TRADEMARKS SEEN AS IMMORAL OR
SCANDALOUS WAS AN UNCONSTITUTIONAL RESTRICTION OF
FREEDOM OF SPEECH. >> TODAY DIKES ON BIKES BOASTS
22 CHAPTERS ACROSS THE UNITED STATES AND AROUND THE WORLD
WITH SAN FRANCISCO DIKES ON BIKES SERVING AS THE MOTHER
CHAPTER CHAPTERS GO ON RIDES THROUGHOUT THE YEAR AND IN THE
MONTHS LEADING UP TO JUNE WORK TO RECRUIT AND ORGANIZE
VOLUNTEERS FOR THE PARADE OR PARADES.
THE ORGANIZATION ALSO HOSTS PRIDE EVENTS AND CELEBRATIONS
ARCHIVES LGBTQ PLUS HISTORY FUNDRAISERS FOR CHARITY
AND PROVIDES EDUCATIONAL PROGRAMS ON MOTORCYCLE RIDING.
>> AS DIKES ON BIKES CELEBRATES ITS 50TH ANNIVERSARY THIS YEAR
,I WANTED TO HONOR THE ORGANIZATION AND CELEBRATE ALL
THE WORK AND ALL THE JOY THE DIKES ON BIKES GENERATIONS OF
THEM HAVE BROUGHT TO THE COMMUNITY AND THE BROADER
COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO AND AROUND THE WORLD.
AND WITHOUT PRESIDENT BROWN THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. PRESIDENT MANCHIN, MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD AND EVERYONE GATHERED HERE TODAY.
I AM DEEPLY HONORED TO ACCEPT THIS COMMENDATION ON BEHALF OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO DIKES ON BIKES WOMEN'S MOTORCYCLE
CONTINGENT OUR MEMBERS, OUR BOARD OF DIRECTORS, OUR
EMERITUS MEMBERS EVERY RIDER WHO HAS CARRIED THIS LEGACY
FORWARD OVER THE LAST 50 YEARS TO BE RECOGNIZED HERE IN THE
CITY OF CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO MEANS MORE THAN I CAN
FULLY EXPRESS. SAN FRANCISCO IS NOT JUST WHERE
OUR ORGANIZATION BEGAN. IT IS THE PLACE WHERE A BOLD
ACT OF VISIBILITY BECAME A MOVEMENT.
>> 50 YEARS AGO A GROUP OF DIKES AND WE'RE GOING TO USE
THAT WORD FREQUENTLY A GROUP OF DIKES MOVED THEIR MOTORCYCLES
TO THE FRONT OF A GAY FREEDOM DAY PARADE AND THEY CLAIMED
SPACE THEY CLAIMED DIGNITY AND THEY CLAIMED JOY AND A
WORLD THAT TOO OFTEN TOLD THEM TO BE SILENT AND INVISIBLE.
>> THAT ACT OF COURAGE BECAME TRADITION.
THAT TRADITION BECAME A COMMUNITY.
>> AND FROM HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THE SAN FRANCISCO
DIKES ON BIKES BECAME THE NONPROFIT MOTHER CHAPTER OF
DIKES ON BIKES THROUGHOUT THE UNITED STATES AND AROUND THE
WORLD. >> EACH CHAPTER OPERATES WITH A
UNIFIED MISSION OF REACHING OUT TO EMPOWER A COMMUNITY OF
DIVERSE RIDERS THROUGH RIDES, CHARITY EVENTS, PRIDE EVENTS
AND EDUCATION ABOUT LGBT CULTURE AND CIVIL RIGHTS.
AS PRESIDENT MANUELIAN SAID THOUGH, OUR HISTORY IS ALSO A
HISTORY OF FIGHTING TO PROTECT OUR NAME AND OUR LOGO AND OUR
RIGHT TO DEFINE OURSELVES. THAT FIGHT TOOK 13 YEARS 13
YEARS AND TWO TRIPS TO THE UNITED STATES SUPREME COURT
CULMINATING IN THE 2017 CASE OF MATTEL VERSUS TAM WHERE WE DID
INDEED HELP OVERTURN A LAW IN A MAJOR WIN FOR LGBTQ COMMUNITY
AND FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION. >> AND I'LL SAY THAT WE WOULD
NOT BE HERE WITHOUT THE POWER OF COMMUNITY INCLUDING BROOKE
OLIVER, OUR GENERAL COUNSEL WHO LED THAT LEGAL STRATEGY AND PRO
BONO FOUGHT THAT BATTLE AND THE MANY LAWYERS AND SCHOLARS WHO
HELPED THE WORLD UNDERSTAND THAT WHEN WE CALL OURSELVES
DIKES, WHEN WE CALL OURSELVES DIKES ON BIKES, WE DO SO WITH
PRIDE. >> WE ARE RECLAIM ING THAT
WORD. >> WE ARE TRANSFORMING AN
EPITHET INTO A SYMBOL OF PRIDE, POWER AND RECLAIMED IDENTITY.
>> EVERY TIME WE PUT THIS PATCH ON OUR BACKS WE ARE ENGAGING
IN AN ACT OF POLITICAL SPEECH. >> WE ARE CARRYING THE COURAGE
OF VISIBILITY. WE ARE HONORING THOSE WHO CAME
BEFORE US. PROTECTING THOSE RIDING BESIDE
US AND MAKING SPACE FOR THOSE WHO WILL COME AFTER US.
>> AND EVERY PRIDE THAT COURAGE IS HEARD BEFORE IT IS EVEN
SEEN. >> REVVING ENGINES, LOUD PIPES
CHEERING PASSENGERS AND THE DEAFENING ROAR OF HUNDREDS OF
MOTORCYCLES COMING DOWN MARKET STREET.
>> THE ICONIC IMAGE OF REBELLIOUS INDEPENDENT BIKES
RIDING POWERFUL MOTORCYCLES HAS BEEN REPEATED IN PRIDE PARADES
THE WORLD OVER CREATING A GLOBAL THUNDEROUS CACOPHONY OF
NOISE AND A RALLYING CRY FOR MOTORCYCLISTS EVERYWHERE.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO DIKES ON BIKES, THANK
YOU FOR SEEING US HONORING US, HEARING US AND CELEBRATING THIS
REMARKABLE MILESTONE WITH US. >> THANK YOU.
>> BEFORE WE GO, YOU AND I ARE HERE TO HAVE EVERYBODY ELSE
AROUND. HELLO RIDING IN YOUR PHOTO
ALBUM. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR
. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
COMMITTEE REPORTS. PLEASE CALL ADAMS 33 TO 36
TOGETHER. >> YES.
ITEM 33 THROUGH 36. WE'RE CONSIDERED BY THE
GOVERNMENT AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
ON THURSDAY, JUNE 4TH, 2026 AND WE'RE FORWARDED AS
COMMITTEE REPORTS. THEREFORE ORDINANCES REGARDING
CERTAIN MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDINGS BETWEEN THE CITY
AND VARIOUS UNIONS. ITEM 33 ADOPTS AND IMPLEMENTS
AN MOU WITH THE MUNICIPAL EXECUTIVES ASSOCIATION FIRE TO
BE EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST, 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030.
ITEM 34 ADOPTS THE MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING WITH THE
MUNICIPAL EXECUTIVES ASSOCIATION POLICE TO BE
EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030.
ITEM 35 FIXES COMPENSATION FOR PERSONS EMPLOYED BY THE CITY
WHOSE COMPENSATION IS SUBJECT TO THE PROVISIONS OF SECTION
8.409 OF THE CHARTER AND JOB CODES NOT REPRESENTED BY AN
EMPLOYEE ORGANIZATION AND ESTABLISHING WORK SCHEDULES
AND OTHER TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF EMPLOYMENT AND METHODS OF
PAYMENT EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST, 2026 AND ITEM 36 IS AN
ORDINANCE THAT ADOPTS AND IMPLEMENTS THE FIRST
AMENDMENT TO THE 2024 TO 2027 MOU WITH THE MACHINISTS UNION
LOCAL 1414 INTERNATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF MACHINISTS
AND AEROSPACE WORKERS MACHINISTS AUTOMOTIVE TRADES
DISTRICT LODGE 190. EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST, 2026 AND TO
ADOPT A SIDE LETTER AGREEMENT UPDATING THE APPENDIX D
APPRENTICESHIP PROGRAM. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
THESE ITEMS AN ITEM 33 TO 36 SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
AUDIENCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 37 YES ITEM 37 WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED WITH THE
SAME TITLE WITH A NEW TITLE TO ADD THE DATE AND TIME OF THE
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE. IT IS A RESOLUTION OF INTENTION
TO ADD TERRITORY TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
INFRASTRUCTURE AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT NUMBER ONE TREASURE ISLAND AS NEW PROJECT AREAS
ORDERING AND SETTING A TIME AND PLACE FOR A PUBLIC HEARING
OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE ON THE PROPOSED ANNEXATION ON SEPTEMBER 15TH
2026 AT 3:00 PM AND TO PROVIDE PUBLIC NOTICE THEREOF I THINK
WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
MR. PRESIDENT WE RETURN GO BACK.
YES MY APOLOGIES MEMBERS AND MR. PRESIDENT I DID READ
THE WRONG TITLE FOR CIP FOR ITEM NUMBER 11 SO WE'RE GOING
TO RECALL THAT. WHEN ARE WE GOING TO RESTATE
IT? >> ITEM 11 IS AN ORDINANCE
APPROVING AMENDED SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICIES FOR PUBLIC
WORKS USE OF UNMANNED AERIAL DEVICES AND USE OF AN ILLEGAL
DUMPING CAMERA SYSTEM WITH AUTOMATIC LICENSE PLATE READER
TECHNOLOGY AND CAMERAS AND MAKING REQUIRED FINDINGS
IN SUPPORT OF STATE APPROVALS. >> AND LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. >> NOW LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL.
FIRST UP FOR ROLL CALL IS SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
I'D LIKE TO BE REFERRED TO. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M INTRODUCING THE NO HIDDEN RENT
ACT BECAUSE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO IS EXPENSIVE ENOUGH
AS IT IS WITHOUT SURPRISES CHARGES, HIDDEN FEES AND FINE
PRINT COSTS THAT LEAVE RENTERS PAYING FAR MORE THAN THEY
EXPECTED. >> FOR MOST PEOPLE RENT IS THE
SINGLE LARGEST EXPENSE THEY FACE EVERY MONTH.
FAMILIES BUDGET AROUND IT WORKERS TAKE EXTRA SHIFTS
BECAUSE OF IT. YOUNG PEOPLE DELAY MAJOR LIFE
DECISIONS BECAUSE OF RENT COSTS.
AND SENIORS ON FIXED INCOMES WORRY ABOUT THEIR ABILITY TO
PAY IT. >> AND YET AFTER ALL THAT
PLANNING AND SACRIFICE, TOO MANY RENTERS DISCOVER THE PRICE
THEY SAW ADVERTISED ISN'T ACTUALLY THE PRICE THEY'LL PAY.
A LISTING WILL SAY ONE THING BUT THE LEASE SAYS ANOTHER.
THEN COMES MANDATORY FEES, AMENITY FEES, ADMINISTRATIVE
FEES AND MY FAVORITE THE TRASH CONCIERGE FEE.
I DON'T KNOW IF ANYONE ELSE HAS HAD A TRASH CONCIERGE BEFORE.
>> I HAVE NOT BUT CHARGES THAT APPEAR ON ONLY AFTER SOMEONE
HAS INVESTED TIME SUBMIT AN APPLICATION AND SIGN ON THE
DOTTED LINE AND EMOTIONALLY COMMITTED TO A HOME.
THAT ISN'T TRANSPARENCY. IT ISN'T FAIRNESS AND IT
CERTAINLY ISN'T HELPING PEOPLE COMMIT TO A LIFE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THE REALITY IS THAT WE'RE
LIVING THROUGH AN AFFORDABILITY CRISIS.
>> PEOPLE ARE STRETCHING EVERY DOLLAR JUST TO REMAIN IN THE
CITY THEY LOVE. THEY SHOULDN'T NEED A
CALCULATOR, A LAWYER OR A MAGNIFYING GLASS JUST TO FIGURE
OUT WHAT THEIR RENT WILL ACTUALLY COST.
THE PRINCIPLE BEHIND THE NO HIDDEN RIGHT ACT IS SIMPLE.
WHEN SOMEONE LOOKS FOR A HOME THEY DESERVE TO KNOW THE REAL
PRICE ONE NUMBER UPFRONT BEFORE THEY APPLY, BEFORE THEY SIGN
AND BEFORE THEY MOVE IN. AND THAT'S WHAT THE NO HIDDEN
RENT ACT DOES. >> IT REQUIRES LANDLORDS TO
CLEARLY DISCLOSE THE TOTAL ESTIMATED COST OF RENTING A
UNIT INCLUDING RECURRING FEES AND CHARGES SO TENANTS CAN MAKE
INFORMED DECISIONS ABOUT WHAT THEY CAN ACTUALLY AFFORD.
>> THIS ISN'T ABOUT CREATING NEW COSTS.
IT'S ABOUT HONESTY AND TRANSPARENCY.
AND IT'S ABOUT GIVING RENTERS THE INFORMATION THEY NEED TO
MAKE ONE OF THE BIGGEST FINANCIAL DECISIONS OF THEIR
LIVES. I'M ESPECIALLY GRATEFUL TO THE
ADVOCATES WHO ARE SUPPORTING THIS BECAUSE THEY SEE FIRSTHAND
WHAT HAPPENS WHEN PEOPLE ARE PUSHED BEYOND THE EDGE
FINANCIALLY. THEY SEE FAMILIES STRUGGLING TO
STAY HOUSED. THEY SEE WORKERS STRUGGLING
MULTIPLE JOBS TO MAKE ENDS MEET.
THEY SEE TENANTS FACING EVICTION OVER CHARGES THEY
DIDN'T FULLY UNDERSTAND WHEN THEY SIGNED A LEASE.
IN A CITY WHERE HOUSING COSTS ARE ALREADY AMONG THE HIGHEST
IN THE NATION, EVERY DOLLAR MATTERS AT A TIME WHEN MANY
LONG TERM HOUSING SOLUTIONS TAKE YEARS TO BUILD IMPLEMENT.
WE ALSO HAVE A RESPONSIBLE CITY TO PURSUE PRACTICAL CHANGES
THAT CAN MAKE RENTING FAIRER NOW THIS LEGISLATION WON'T
SOLVE THE HOUSING CRISIS ON ITS OWN BUT IT WILL MAKE THE SYSTEM
MORE HONEST. IT WILL MAKE THE MARKET MORE
TRANSPARENT AND IT WILL HELP ENSURE THAT THE ADVERTISED
PRICE OF HOUSING IS THE REAL PRICE OF HOUSING.
BECAUSE AT THE END OF THE DAY TENANTS DESERVE CLARITY
AND THEY DESERVE THE ABILITY TO PLAN FOR THEIR FUTURE WITHOUT
WORRYING ABOUT HIDDEN COSTS WHILE WAITING AROUND THE CORNER
. I WANT TO THANK THE INCREDIBLE
PEOPLE AND ORGANIZATIONS WHO HELPED CONSULT ON THIS
LEGISLATION. THANK YOU TO GAIL GILMAN WHERE
OUR PROJECT OFF NICK PROPTECH AND THE EVICTION DEFENSE
COLLABORATIVE WHOSE WORK EVERY DAY HELPS SAN FRANCISCANS HOUSE
AND PREVENTS HOMELESSNESS BEFORE IT STARTS.
THANK YOU TO ALL OF MIRANDA AND SEIU LOCAL 87 FOR BEING
RELENTLESS CHAMPIONS FOR WORKING FAMILIES, IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITIES AND THE WORKERS WHO KEEP OUR CITY RUNNING.
THANK YOU TO RECEIVE A TECHIE AND TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC
FOR THEIR TIRELESS ADVOCACY ON BEHALF OF TENANTS ACROSS SAN
FRANCISCO. THANK YOU TO MY CHIEF OF STAFF
SAM LOGAN FOR HER COMMITMENT IN CARRYING THIS LEGISLATION.
AND THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR SADR MELGAR AND CHEN FOR THEIR
EARLY PARTNERSHIP AND SUPPORT OF THIS LEGISLATION.
>> THANK YOU AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE A COUPLE OF ITEMS TWO ORDINANCES.
>> FIRST, I'M INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO EXPAND THE CURRENT
FEE WAIVER FOR BANNER PERMITS TO INCLUDE ORGANIZATIONS
IN NEIGHBORHOOD OF COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS, NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL TRANSIT DISTRICTS AND AND RESIDENTIAL TRANSIT
ORIENTED COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS CITYWIDE BANNERS ON CITY OWNED
UTILITY POLES ARE A SIMPLE AND EFFECTIVE TOOL FOR
PLACEMENT MAKING. THEY SIGNAL NEIGHBORHOOD
IDENTITY CELEBRATE COMMUNITY EVENTS AND GIVE COMMERCIAL
CORRIDORS A SENSE OF CHARACTER AND COHESION.
BUT MANY OF THE COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS THAT CONTRIBUTE
SO MUCH TO OUR CULTURAL SPACES CANNOT AFFORD THE FEES
ASSOCIATED WITH THESE BANNERS. >> UNDER CURRENT LAW, BANNER
PERMIT AND INSPECTION FEES ARE WAIVED BUT ONLY FOR SELECT
ORGANIZATIONS. >> IN 2020 THREE SUPERVISOR
DORSEY PASSED LEGISLATION TO WAIVE FEES FOR SOMA PILIPINAS
AND THE LEATHER AND LGBTQ CULTURAL DISTRICT IN 2024
FORMER SUPERVISOR PRESTON PASSED LEGISLATION TO WAIVE
FEES FOR NONPROFITS AND COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS
IN DISTRICT FIVE. THIS ORDINANCE WOULD EXTEND
THAT FEE WAIVER TO ELIGIBLE COMMUNITY BASED NONPROFITS
IN EVERY NCD AND TDI AND ARTO DASHTI DISTRICT IN THE CITY.
IT WOULD MAKE THE PROGRAM PERMANENT AND INCREASE THE
ANNUAL ORGANIZATIONAL BUDGET ELIGIBILITY THRESHOLD FROM
$250,000 TO $500,000 REFLECTING THE REALITY OF WHAT IT COSTS TO
RUN A COMMUNITY ORGANIZATION. >> TODAY I WANT TO THANK TERRY
AUSTIN BENNETT FROM THE CASTRO MERCHANTS FOR BRINGING THIS
ISSUE TO OUR OFFICES ATTENTION. I WANT TO THANK PETER MILLION
FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR HIS WORK AND I WANT TO
THANK MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE RENE AUBERJONOIS FOR HIS WORK AS
WELL. >> SECONDLY, I'M INTRODUCING
ORDINANCE TO EXPAND THE EXISTING FEE WAIVER PROGRAM FOR
PROPERTY OWNERS PARTICIPATING IN THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTIONS INTERNAL QUALITY CONTROL AUDIT AMNESTY PROGRAM.
AND SPECIFICALLY WE ARE PROPOSING TO WAIVE FIRE CODE
AND PUBLIC WORKS CODE FEES. >> LAST YEAR THE BOARD PASSED
LEGISLATION TO ESTABLISH THAT AT AUDIT AMNESTY PROGRAM TO
WAIVE BUILDING AND PLANNING CODE FEES FOR PROPERTY OWNERS
UNWITTINGLY CAUGHT UP IN THE AFTER MATH OF THE CORRUPTION
SCANDAL AT TBI INVOLVING PERMIT EXPEDITER RODRIGO SANTOS
AND FORMER SENIOR BUILDING INSPECTOR BERNIE CURRAN MOST OF
THE PROPERTY OWNERS WHO WERE HIT WITH NOTICES OF VIOLATION
BASED ON THE DEBES REVIEW OF PROPERTIES THAT HAD BEEN
TOUCHED BY SANTOS AND CURRAN BOUGHT THEIR PROPERTIES LONG
AFTER THE PERMITTED UNPERMITTED WORK WAS COMPLETED AND WERE
COMPLETELY UNAWARE THAT THEY MIGHT HAVE VIOLATIONS.
>> THE IN THE COURSE OF SO WE WAIVED AS I SAID THE PLANNING
AND BUILDING CODE FEES BUT IN THE COURSE OF COMMUNICATING
WITH THESE PROPERTY OWNERS OVER THE PAST YEAR WE'VE IDENTIFIED
ADDITIONAL CITY FEES ASSOCIATED WITH THE PERMITS THAT ARE
NEEDED TO BRING THEIR PROPERTIES IN COMPLIANCE WITH
THE BUILDING CODE AND ACCORDINGLY ACCORDINGLY
THIS ORDINANCE WOULD WAIVE PLAN REVIEW ADMINISTRATIVE
AND INSPECTION FEES FOR PUBLIC WORKS AND FIRE DEPARTMENT
PERMITS UNDER THE AUDIT AMNESTY PROGRAM.
LIKE THE PREVIOUS LEGISLATION, THESE WAIVERS WOULD BE
RETROACTIVE AND WE WOULD REFUND FEES TO THOSE WHO'VE ALREADY
PAID. >> I WANT TO THANK ROB COPPOLA
AT THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR HIS WORK TO HANNA
AND FERGAL CLANCY AT TBI. IAN SCHNEIDER AT PUBLIC WORKS.
KATHY HEROLD AT THE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND MY LEGISLATIVE
AIDE AGAIN RENE AUBERJONOIS FOR ALL OF THEIR WORK AND THE REST
I SUBMIT THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MILLER THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE TWO ITEMS TO INTRODUCE RELATED TO
KEEPING OUR STREETS SIDEWALK AND PUBLIC SPACES CLEAN.
>> FIRST I'M INTRODUCING LEGISLATION THAT WILL ALLOW
PUBLIC WORKS TO PURSUE COST RECOVERY WHEN THEY ENFORCE A
LEGAL DUMPING VIOLATIONS. AS IT CURRENTLY STANDS SAN
FRANCISCO'S MAXIMUM ALLOWABLE FINE IS $1,000 FOR LEGAL
DUMPING VIOLATIONS. BUT THE TRUE COST TO OUR CITY
IS FAR MORE COMPLEX FOR CLEANUPS FOR FOR LARGER
VIOLATIONS WHICH OFTEN INVOLVE HAZARDOUS WASTE BULK INDUSTRIAL
ITEMS OR LARGE CONSTRUCTION MATERIALS.
THESE COSTS FROM QUICKLY CLIMB TO THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS IN CITY
STAFFING, TIME AND RESOURCES. OUR LEGISLATION MAKES
AMENDMENTS TO ARTICLE 26 OF THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE AND SEEKS TO
BRING THE TRUE CLEANUP COSTS AND VIOLATIONS MORE IN LINE.
COST RECOVERY WILL ALLOW US TO FORCE VIOLATORS TO PAY FOR THE
TRUE COST OF CLEANUP, INVESTIGATION AND DISPOSAL OF
UNAUTHORIZED WASTE. 2024 DATA SHOWS THAT DISTRICT
THREE HAS THE MOST SERVICE REQUESTS FOR LEGAL DUMPING OF
ANY DISTRICT. WHILE MANY OF THESE REQUESTS
ARE FOR SMALL ITEMS OR OVERFLOWING TRASH CANS, WE
STILL HAD APPROXIMATELY 7000 CASES OF A LARGER VIOLATIONS.
>> WE NEED TO MAKE PROGRESS ON THIS AND I'M OPTIMISTIC THAT
THIS NEW TOOL WILL HELP. THIS COST RECOVERY MODEL
DOESN'T LEAD WITH SUBJECTIVE PUNITIVE FINES BUT RATHER
ALIGNS THE TRUE COST OF CLEANUP WITH THE VIOLATION ITSELF.
AND THIS IS A COMMON PRACTICE IN MOST MAJOR CITIES.
>> AND AS WE GIVE PUBLIC WORKS MORE TOOLS IT IS REASONABLE
THAT WE SHOULD ALSO EXPECT BETTER RESULTS.
SO TODAY I AM CALLING FOR A HEARING ON ILLEGAL DUMPING
ENFORCEMENT IN SAN FRANCISCO AS WELL.
IN OUR HEARING WE WILL EXAMINE HOW OUR CURRENT ENFORCEMENT
EFFORTS ARE GOING AND SEE WHERE THEY FALL SHORT.
AN OCTOBER 2025 PERFORMANCE AUDIT FROM THE BLM SHED LIGHT
ON THIS CALLING CURRENT EFFORTS TO ENFORCE ILLEGAL DUMPING
INSUFFICIENT. THE REPORT NOTED THAT ILLEGAL
DUMPING FINES ARE TOO OFTEN NOT PURSUED OR COLLECTED AND THAT
ENFORCEMENT ACTIVITY REMAINS BELOW PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS.
THE BLM ALSO OUTLINED FIVE SPECIFIC RECOMMENDATIONS THAT
WE INTEND TO ASK FOR UPDATES ON OUR CITY'S STREETS, SIDEWALKS
AND PUBLIC SPACES SHOULD BE CLEANED CLEAR AND SAFE FOR ALL
THOSE TO MOVE ABOUT AND ENJOY. AND OUR INTRODUCTION OF THESE
TWO ITEMS TODAY WILL HELP MOVE US TOWARDS MEETING THAT VERY
GOAL. THANK YOU TO MY CHIEF OF STAFF
TO TO BELL FOR HER WORK ON BOTH OF THESE ITEMS.
AND THANKS TO CITY ATTORNEY CHRIS TOM FOR HIS WORK TO DRAFT
OUR LEGISLATION. >> AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR SHERYL.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF KENT JONES, A
RETIRE 17 YEAR VETERAN OF THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
WHO PASSED AWAY FROM WORK RELATED LUNG CANCER ON MAY 30TH
OF 2026. CAN JOIN THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
DEPARTMENT IN 1995 SEEKING MEANINGFUL WORK AND OPPORTUNITY
TO USE HIS SKILLS IN SERVICE TO THE COMMUNITY.
HE WAS KNOWN FOR HIS COMMITMENT TO CONTINUING LI IMPROVING HIS
FIREFIGHTING AND MEDICAL EXPERTISE, STRONG WORK ETHIC
AND THE KINDNESS AND GOOD HUMOR HE BROUGHT TO THE FIREHOUSE.
IN A LATER YEARS OF HIS CAREER, KEN HELPED REVITALIZE THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT'S BEHAVIORAL HEALTH UNIT THEN KNOWN AS THE STRESS
UNIT. HE DEVOTED BOTH HIS TIME
AND HIS HEART TO SUPPORTING FELLOW MEMBERS THROUGH SOME OF
THE PROFESSION'S MOST DIFFICULT CHALLENGES.
THE SUPPORT INCLUDED HELPING MEMBERS TO COPE WITH THE TRAUMA
OF RESPONDING TO INCIDENTS INVOLVING CIVILIANS DEATHS,
FIREFIGHTER INJURIES AND FATALITIES AND HARM TO
CHILDREN. KEN HAD A RARE GIFT FOR MAKING
PEOPLE FEEL HURT AND RESPECTED AND MEMBERS FROM ALL WALKS OF
LIFE TRUSTED HIM WITH THEIR STRUGGLES.
KEN'S CANCER TREATMENT WAS COMPLICATED BY BLUE SHIELD'S
DENIAL OF COVERAGE FOR MEDICATIONS THAT HIS UCSF
ONCOLOGISTS BELIEVE OFFERED THE BEST CHANCE OF EXTENDING HIS
LIFE. THOUGH SPEAKING PUBLICLY ABOUT
THOSE CHALLENGES BROUGHT HIM NO PERSONAL BENEFIT, HE CHOSE TO
DO SO IN THE HOPE THAT GREATER AWARENESS MIGHT LEAD TO CHANGES
THAT WOULD HELP OTHERS FACING SIMILAR CIRCUMSTANCES.
HE ULTIMATELY RECEIVED APPROPRIATE TREATMENT ONLY
AFTER LEAVING BLUE SHIELD. KEN JONES WILL BE REMEMBERED AS
A MAN OF SERVICE, INTEGRITY, COMPASSION AND HUMOR.
HE LOVED HIS FAMILY, HIS COLLEAGUES AND HIS COMMUNITY
DEEPLY. AND I WOULD ADD HE LOVES SAN
FRAN. HE LOVED SAN FRANCISCO DEEPLY
AND HE MADE A LASTING DIFFERENCE IN THE LIVES OF
COUNTLESS PEOPLE. HIS LEGACY WILL ENDURE THE
LIVES OF THOSE WHO HE SERVED, SUPPORTED AND INSPIRE.
>> THANK YOU. >> WOULD YOU MIND IF WE DO THAT
ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD? ABSOLUTELY.
AND I KNOW THAT SUPERVISOR DORSEY WOULD ALSO LIKE TO ADD
TO THIS TOO IF HE CAN BE WE REFER NOW.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
I WANTED TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR A BEAUTIFUL AND MOVING
TRIBUTE TO THE LATE KEN JONES AND ADD MY OWN CONDOLENCES TO
HIS WIFE AND FAMILY MEMBERS AND LOVED ONES AS WELL AS TO
THE FIREFIGHTERS OF LOCAL 798 AS THE BOARD REPRESENTATIVE TO
THE HEALTH SERVICE SYSTEM I HAD A ROLE TO PLAY AT A HEARING
AND SOME OTHER EFFORTS TO GET TO THE BOTTOM OF DENIALS OF
CARE BY BLUE SHIELD OF CALIFORNIA THAT KEN JONES
EXPERIENCED IN LARGE PART FOR ME THAT MEANT RIDING SHOTGUN TO
BUDGET CHAIR CONNIE CHAN AND I THANK YOU CHAIR CHAN FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP ON THAT. THROUGHOUT THAT PROCESS
HOWEVER, I WAS CONTINUALLY MOVED AND INSPIRED BY KEN'S
COMMITMENT TO MAKING SURE THAT THE HARDSHIPS HE AND HIS FAMILY
FACED WOULD NOT BE FACED BY OTHER PATIENTS AND THEIR
FAMILIES IN A LIFETIME DISTINGUISHED BY HEROIC PUBLIC
SERVICE. KEN JONES EXEMPLARY ADVOCACY TO
THE VERY END OF HIS LIFE MADE AN IMPORTANT DIFFERENCE AND I
WAS GRATEFUL TO READ THAT BLUE SHIELD IS NOW ENGAGING WITH SAN
FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTERS AND OTHER ADVOCATES TO EXPLORE
INSURANCE POLICY REFORMS TO ENSURE THAT FIRST RESPONDERS
ARE NEVER AGAIN LEFT WITHOUT CRITICAL MEDICAL CARE.
SO I'D LIKE TO BE ADDED AS WELL TO THE IN MEMORIAM OFFERED BY
SUPERVISOR CHAN AND JUST SAY REST IN PEACE.
KEN JONES. AND WE'LL HAVE THAT ON BEHALF
OF THE FULL BOARD. >> OKAY.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU MADAM
CLERK. COLLEAGUE TODAY I'M PROUD TO
INTRODUCE OUR RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING JUNE 19TH, 2026 AS
THE DRAGON BALL FESTIVAL DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO AND SUPPORTING
ASSEMBLY CONCURRENT RESOLUTION 123 WHICH RECOGNIZE THE SAME
DAY A STRONG WOULD YET THROUGHOUT THE STATE OF
CALIFORNIA AS A CHINESE-AMERICAN THE DAUGHTER
OF IMMIGRANT FROM GUANGDONG AND THE PROUD REPRESENTATIVE OF
ONE OF THE MOST DIVERSE CITY IN THE WORLD.
AND IT'S ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL TO CELEBRATE A TRADITION THAT
HAS CONNECTED GENERATIONS OF CHINESE FAMILY AND COMMUNITIES
FOR MORE THAN 2000 YEARS. THE DRAGON BOAT FESTIVAL OR
DOGWOODS YET IT'S ONE OF THE MOST CHERISHED STATE HOLIDAYS
IN CHINESE CULTURE OBSERVED ON THE FIFTH DAY OF THE FIFTH
MONTH OF NOON AND AFTERNOON AND CALENDAR.
IT'S A CELEBRATION OF RICH WIT, HISTORY, SYMBOLISM
AND COMMUNITY SPIRIT ACROSS GENERATIONS.
FAMILY GATHER TO MAKE AND SHARE JOINT STICKY RICE WRAPPED IT
IN BAMBOO LEAVES TRADITIONAL HERBS ARE HANG TO PROMOTE
HEALTH AND WELL-BEING. MOST FAMOUSLY COMMUNITIES COME
TOGETHER FOR DRAGON BOAT RACE A VIBRANT SPORT THAT EMBODIES
TEAMWORK, PERSEVERANCE, DISCIPLINE AND COLLECTIVE
STRENGTH. THE DRAGON ITSELF IT'S A
POWERFUL SYMBOL IN CHINESE CULTURE REPRESENTING COURAGE,
PROSPERITY, RESILIENCE AND GOOD FORTUNE.
THIS VALUES RESONATE DEEPLY WITH THE SPIRITS OF SAN
FRANCISCO, A CITY BUILT BY IMMIGRANTS STRENGTHENED BY
DIVERSITY AND UNITED BY BELIEF THAT OUR DIFFERENT CULTURES
MAKE US STRONGER TOGETHER. DRAGON BOAT FESTIVAL IS MORE
THAN A HOLIDAY. IT'S A LIVING EXPRESSIONS OF
CULTURE, IDENTITY AND HERITAGE. IT REMINDS US THAT PRESERVING
TRADITION IS NOT ONLY ABOUT LOOKING BETTER, IT'S ABOUT
CARRYING FORWARD THE STORIES, THE VALUES, THE CONNECTION THAT
SHAPE WHO WE ARE AND ENRICH THE COMMUNITIES WE ARE ALL CALLED
HOME. THIS YEAR WE ARE ESPECIALLY
HONOR THAT THE CALIFORNIA DRAGON BOAT ASSOCIATION WILL
HOST A NORTHERN CALIFORNIA INTERNATIONAL DRAGON BOAT
FESTIVAL AT LINK SET RIGHT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
ATHLETES FAMILIES AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS FROM ACROSS THE REGION
WILL GATHER TO CELEBRATE NOT ONLY A BELOVED CULTURE
TRADITION BUT ALSO THE UNIVERSAL VALUES OF TEAMWORK,
SPORTSMANSHIP AND COMMUNITY PRIDE.
IN SAN FRANCISCO WE CELEBRATE THE MANY CULTURES THAT
CONTRIBUTE TO THE FABRIC OF OUR CITY.
RECOGNIZING DRAGON BOAT FESTIVAL DAY AFFIRMS OUR
COMMITMENT TO HONORING CULTURAL HERITAGE, EMBRACING DIVERSITY
AND ENSURING THAT EVERY COMMUNITY SEES ITS TRADITION
REFLECTED IN THE STORY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS RESOLUTION
AND I WOULD LIKE TO THANK OUR CO-SPONSORSHIP WHICH IS EVERY
ONE OF YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHEN. MR. PRESIDENT, SEE NO OTHER
NAMES ON THE ROSTER. >> THAT CONCLUDES ROLL CALL FOR
INTRODUCTIONS. LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG
THE CURTAINS. YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MAYOR'S
APPEARANCE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
ITEMS 40 THROUGH 59 THE ITEMS ON THE FLOOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA AND GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE
PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION. >> ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT
WILL HAVE BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE
COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT REQUIREMENT OCCURRED.
>> WILL THE FIRST SPEAKER COME FORWARD?
>> EVERYONE WILL BE PROVIDED THE SAME TWO MINUTES.
>> HELLO. GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY.
SO MY NAME IS HENRY FROM COMMITTEE YOUTH CENTER AND ON
BEHALF OF COMMITTEES CENTER AND CALIFORNIA DRY BALL
ASSOCIATION AND THE DRAGON WILL COMMITTEE WILL BE APPRECIATED
FIRST OF ALL WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU THE SUPERVISORS
LUNCHEON AND ALSO EVERYBODY THAT WILL BE SUPPORTIVE ABOUT
THIS TANGLEWOOD DRAGON BOAT FESTIVAL AND JUST IN LEGEND NOW
THAT DIANE WILL HAVE BEEN. 2000 THE 500 YEARS OF HISTORY
AND WE WILL BE FORTUNATE THAT WE CAN HOST THE DRAGON BOAT
RACE IN SAN FRANCISCO A LAKE MASS THAT LIKE WHAT SUPERVISORS
ARE IN CHARGE AND SAY THAT THIS IS AN OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO
BRING THE WHOLE JONESVILLE COMMUNITY AND THE COMMUNITY
AND COME OUT THIS EVENT TO CELEBRATE THE HISTORY OF DRAGON
BOAT AND ALSO GET TO KNOW EACH OTHER.
SO THE THEME OF THE DRAGON BOAT IS TO RAISE A CHILD IS CALLED
YE LONG WAY OUT IS ABOUT THE FRIENDSHIP THROUGH WITH THE
DRAGONS. SO ON THAT DAY WE HAVE 40 TEAMS
FROM THE COMMUNITY TEAM FROM HIGH SCHOOL AND ALSO FROM SOME
CORPORATE SAMPLE FASHION SHOW TEAM AND THEY ALL JOIN TOGETHER
TO HAVE A FRIENDLY RACE ON SATURDAY AND SUNDAY AND THEY
WILL IMPORTANT ARE REALLY IMPORTANT THAT WE WILL BE HAPPY
TO KNOW THIS BECAUSE DRAGON BALL IN SAN FRANCISCO HAVE MORE
THAN 30 YEARS OF HISTORY AND WE NEVER GOT RECOGNIZED.
NOT A LOT OF PEOPLE KNOW ABOUT DRAGON BOAT MY FLAG I HAVE
BAILEY AND KEVIN AND ZAC. THEY ARE THE FORMER YOUTH WHEN
THEY PADDLES IN 2013 AND THEY STILL COME BACK TO DAY AS A
DRAGON BALL COACH FOR THE C BAILEY AND THE COACH FOR THE
LINCOLN HIGH SCHOOL AND CONTINUE TO GIVE BACK TO
THE COMMUNITY SO I WILL BE HERE AND WANT TO SAY THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR YOUR SUPPORT EVERYBODY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER I JUST WANT TO CHECK FIRST IS THIS CURRENTLY
WORKING? >> YES IT IS.
OKAY. UM HELLO.
>> I SEE A LOT MORE PUBLIC SUPPORT FOR TRANS PEOPLE THIS
PRIDE WHICH IS GREAT. HOWEVER I DO NOT FORGET WHAT
HAPPENED LAST PRIDE I SUPERVISOR UPON I MADE THIS
COMMENT BECAUSE PEOPLE AT THE TRANS MARCH HECKLED THE
MAYOR AWAY THIS OBNOXIOUS BEHAVIOR DOES NOT REPRESENT SAN
FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ COMMUNITY AND OUR ALLY MAYOR DANIEL LURIE
DESERVES BETTER. >> EVERYONE IN THE LGBTQ
COMMUNITY NEEDS TO START CALLING OUT THIS EMBARRASSING
FRINGE THAT BAD THAT BADLY HURTING THE CAUSE OF LGBTQ PLUS
PROGRESS FOR ALL OF US. YOU KNOW I SOUND LIKE BIGOTRY
OR SOMETHING FOR TRANS PEOPLE THE OTHER DAY AND I GUESS
THAT'S FINE BUT WHEN YOU SHOULD APOLOGIZE TO YOU SHOULD
ACTUALLY PUT FORTH SOME REAL LEGISLATION THAT WILL ACTUALLY
HELP US THE CITY ATTORNEY AND THIS BOARD IN GENERAL ALSO
NEEDS TO ATONE FOR HOW THEY VOTED ON THE GIFT PROGRAM
SETTLEMENTS THAT HAPPENS IN 2024.
>> THAT WAS WHERE THE GIFT PROGRAM WAS A BASIC INCOME
PROGRAM FOR TRANS PEOPLE BLACK AND LATINO TRANS PEOPLE
SPECIFICALLY AND THE SETTLEMENTS FOR BAIT MADE IT
ILLEGAL FOR ANY BASIC INCOME PROGRAMS TO EXIST IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR NOT JUST TRANS PEOPLE BUT BLACK PEOPLE
AND LATINO PEOPLE AS WELL. >> AND I'VE BEEN TRYING TO
FIGURE OUT HOW HOW DO WE RAISE THE STANDARD OF LIVING FOR ALL
THESE PEOPLE. >> WHEN YOU AGREED EXCEPT FOR
SOME ON WALTON DEAN PRESTON AND AARON PESKIN WHO VOTED
AGAINST IT AND BEGGED YOU ALL TO VOTE AGAINST IT BUT ANYWAY
WHEN YOU MADE IT ILLEGAL REPARATIONS THAT WOULD HELP THE
BLACK COMMUNITY BLACK LATINO PEOPLE AND BLACK TRANS PEOPLE.
>> SO FUND THE REPARATIONS. >> I HEAR BILLIONAIRES ARE
DONATING TO OUR GOVERNMENT NOW ,RIGHT?
>> WHY DON'T YOU ASK HIM FOR SOME DONATIONS ON THAT ONE?
OH, NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. HELLO, GLORIA BARRY, FORMER
RESIDENT IN THE 1D4D5 6010 AND NOW I'M IN THE 11.
>> UM I AM HERE ONE THANK YOU FOR MENTIONING REPARATIONS.
I THINK WE DO NEED TO BE MORE CREATIVE AND HOW THAT'S FUNDING
AND ALSO GIVE THE CITY ATTORNEY OFFICE TO AVOID LAWSUITS
AND MOVE FORWARD INSTEAD OF JUST SITTING THE REPARATIONS
ORDINANCE ON A SHELF. >> BUT WHY I'M REALLY HERE IS
UM A LOT OF COMMUNITY MEMBERS THAT I'M REALLY CLOSE TO CAME
BEFORE YOU ABOUT THE ELLA HILL COMMUNITY CENTER ELLA HILL
HUTCH COMMUNITY CENTER IN D FIVE AND WE MADE A BIG IMPACT
ON OUR ON OUR EFFORTS AND EVEN THE CHRONICLE CAME OUT
AND SUPPORTED US AND THE MAYOR REMOVES THE ELLA HILL
HUTCH FROM BEING UNDERNEATH EXACTLY.
>> GIVE DIRECTOR SHAKIRA SMILEY AT BOOKER T COME TO FIND OUT
TODAY SHE STILL GETS THE MONEY BUT NOBODY GETS FUNDED IN THE
CENTER SO NOW PECKINPAH EXCUSE ME PARKS AND REC IS UH,
STRUGGLING TO GET A PROGRAM OPEN MONDAY FOR THE YOUTH WITH
NO FUNDING, NO SCHEDULE, NO FOOD FOR THE CHILDREN, NO FIELD
TRIPS AND SHAKIRA SMILEY IS LOOKING FOR A BUILDING BECAUSE
SHE'S AVOIDING COLLAB READING WITH COMMUNITY MEMBERS AT ELLA
HILL CHURCH. >> THIS IS DISGUSTING.
ONE PERSON'S SHOULDN'T BE THE TRUSTED SOURCE OF THE MAYOR OR
ANYONE ELSE AND PLEASE LISTEN TO THE COMMUNITY YOUR KIDS NEED
PROGRAMING THIS SUMMER. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
MY NAME IS GLORIA LAWRENCE. I'VE BEEN IN SAN FRANCISCO
ABOUT SIX MONTHS. I CAME FROM I'M JUST GOING TO
SAY REAL FAR RIGHT BIBLE BELT AREA WHERE I CAME HERE FOR MY
REFUGE AND ALSO I'M A BIT OF A POLITICAL ACTIVIST HOPING TO
EVENTUALLY GET INTO POLITICS SOMEDAY.
TODAY I'M HERE TO ADDRESS YOU GUYS ON HOPEFULLY BEING ABLE TO
GET SOMETHING DONE ABOUT THE HOMELESS PROGRAMS SPECIFICALLY
THE ABILITY MYSELF BEING HOMELESS.
I AM IN THE NEXT DOOR SHELTER RIGHT NOW.
I'VE BEEN THROWN OUT OF ONE SHELTER FOR FALSE PRETENSES.
I'VE HAD A LOT OF JUST DISCRIMINATION.
THERE'S A LOT OF NEGLIGENCE WITHIN THE FIVE KEY SYSTEM.
I'M NOT HERE THIS TIME TO COMPLAIN ABOUT THE CORRUPTION
AND EVERYTHING BECAUSE I'LL BE REPORTING THAT SEPARATELY.
WHAT I'M HERE TODAY TO TALK TO YOU GUYS ABOUT IS TO ASK YOU TO
CONSIDER THE POSSIBILITY OF I GUESS INSTEAD OF JUST JOBS
AND JUST GIVING PEOPLE LIKE EMPLOYMENT, YOU KNOW,
OPPORTUNITIES AND I GUESS BASIC RESUMÉ WORKSHOPS AND INTERVIEW
ASSISTANTS, WHATEVER. I THINK IT WOULD BE HELPFUL FOR
SO MANY OF US. NOW MANY PEOPLE WOULD PROBABLY
TAKE ADVANTAGE. THAT'S JUST THE WAY IT GOES.
BUT SO MANY OF US WOULD BE ABLE TO SIGNIFICANTLY BENEFIT FROM
BEING ABLE TO OH I DON'T KNOW IF Y'ALL HAVE A SPECIAL PROGRAM
OR COULD CREATE A SPECIAL PROGRAM WHERE LIKE THE CITY
APPRENTICESHIPS SPECIFICALLY FOR AND I DON'T REMEMBER WHAT
IT'S CALLED BUT THE ONES REGARDING LIKE THE TYPES OF
PROGRAMS LIKE 4 OR 5 KEYS AND THE OTHER EMPLOYMENT
ASSISTANCE PROGRAMS WHERE WE CAN GO IN AND INSTEAD OF I
GUESS JUST HOW DO I SAY IT LIKE FOCUSING ON PEOPLE THAT NEED
SHELTER THAT ARE IN THE HOMELESS PROGRAM THEY THANK YOU
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> MY APOLOGIES FOR CUTTING YOU
OFF. WE ARE PROVIDING EVERYONE THE
SAME TWO MINUTES. >> NEXT SPEAKER PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT AND BOARD MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
YOU. YOU PEOPLE ARE SUPPOSED TO BE
THE GREAT ORATORS OF OUR TIME AND WHY CAN'T YOU SPEAK UP?
I MEAN, I HAVE GREAT TROUBLE HEARING YOU AND I HAVE PRETTY
GOOD HEARING AND I NOTICE I CHASTISE SO I THINK I WAS
DISTRICT 11 MEMBER AND NOW HE'S SPEAKING UP SO I HAVE TO GO
AROUND AND CHASTISE EACH ONE OF YOU.
BUT IN THE MEANTIME I'M STILL NOTICING THAT THE SEAT FOR
DISTRICT NINE IS EMPTY AND I'M WONDERING HOW LONG ARE YOU
GOING TO KEEP THIS CHARADE UP WITH THE MAYOR?
I MEAN AND EVENTUALLY YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE TO MAKE A CHOICE
AND EVENTUALLY SUPPOSE THE DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR CAME
BACK UNDER WHAT CONDITIONS IS HE GOING TO COME BACK?
>> DOES SHE HAVE TO GET A NOTE FROM HER DOCTOR?
ARE WE GOING TO BE ASSURED BY THE BE THE PEOPLE GOING TO BE
ASSURED THAT IF SHE'S COMPETENT TO TO LEAD DISTRICT NINE?
>> I DON'T KNOW. THESE ARE QUESTIONS THAT I
THINK YOU'VE GOT YOURSELF INTO A BIND IN ORDER TO ANSWER COME
JUNE 28TH. IS SHE GOING TO COME BACK?
I DON'T KNOW. IS THERE TIME FOR THE MAYOR TO
APPOINT SOMEBODY TO RUN AND IN THE NOVEMBER ELECTIONS I DON'T
KNOW. >> THOSE ARE ALL INTERESTING
QUESTIONS THAT NEED TO BE ANSWERED AND I DON'T SEE THE
BOARD MEMBERS ANSWERING THIS QUESTION AND I DON'T SEE THAT
THE FIGHT WITH THE MAYOR ON KEEPING THE MAYOR'S APPOINTMENT
OUT IS GOING TO HELP MATTERS AT ALL.
SO AGAIN, I'M JUST CONCERNED. >> GOOD LUCK.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO. GOOD EVENING.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ERICA SCOTT AND I AM
ADDRESSING YOU ALL IN REFERENCE TO THE AL-HAJJ COMMUNITY
CENTER. A COUPLE OF COMMUNITY MEMBERS
AND I HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK TO THE MANAGER FROM PARKS
AND REC WHO IS GOING TO OVERSEE PROGRAMING AT THE HILL ELMO
HUTCH COMMUNITY CENTER. AND WE WERE TOLD THAT THERE'S
NOT ACTUAL YOUTH PROGRAMING THAT IS SUPPOSED TO HAPPEN AT
THE SITE. AND WE JUST WANT CLARITY.
WE WANT TRANSPARENCY. WE WANT TO KNOW THE EXACT
PROCESS. SO WHAT EXACTLY IS HAPPENING?
BECAUSE WE WERE TOLD THAT PARK AND REC WAS GOING TO COME IN TO
HOST PROGRAMING. IT'S JUST NOT AS CUT AND DRY AS
IT WAS TOLD TO US AS IT WAS TOLD TO THE PUBLIC.
BOOKER T WASHINGTON COMMUNITY CENTER IS STILL INVOLVED
IN PROGRAMING WHICH AGAIN WE WERE TOLD PUBLICLY THAT WOULD
NOT HAPPEN. >> SO AGAIN I'M JUST SITTING
HERE HOPING THAT WE CAN GET SOME CLEAR ANSWERS
AND INFORMATION. A DEPARTMENT OF PARKS AND REC
THE STAFF THAT WE MET WITH WERE VERY OPEN, VERY WELCOMING TO US
WORKING ALONGSIDE THEM. BUT AGAIN THERE'S POWERS THAT
BE THAT ARE MAKING DECISIONS FOR OUR COMMUNITY AGAIN AND NOT
BEING COMPLETELY TRANSPARENT IN THE PROCESS.
AND WE JUST DON'T WANT SUMMER PROGRAMING TO HAPPEN THAT TURNS
INTO FALL PROGRAMING. AND THEN ONCE AGAIN THE CITY IS
MAKING DECISIONS ON OUR BEHALF. WE THOUGHT WE HAD KIND OF
WORKED TOWARDS A SOLUTION THAT THAT WOULDN'T HAPPEN.
BUT COMMUNITY IS STILL NOT BEING MADE AWARE OF THE ACTUAL
PROCESS. SO I JUST WANTED TO PUT THAT ON
PUBLIC RECORD THAT WE REALLY, REALLY REQUIRE MORE OF AN OPEN
PROCESS AS IT RELATES TO ELMHURST COMMUNITY CENTER.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> BEFORE WE START TIME I JUST
WOULD LIKE TO REQUEST THE ATTENTION OF THE SUPERVISOR ON
STARTING YOUR TIME. >> OKAY.
SO MY NAME IS DANNY CECALA. I AM A RESIDENT LONGTIME
RESIDENT OF THE FILLMORE DISTRICT.
>> AND I'M JUST A LITTLE CONFUSED AS TO WHY TAKING CARE
OF THAT PARTICULAR COMMUNITY IS SUCH A DIFFICULT PROCESS FOR
THIS BODY AND THE BODIES OF THE POLITICAL FIGURES IN THIS CITY.
>> WE SPEND A LOT OF TIME MAKING SURE THAT A LOT OF OTHER
COMMUNITIES ARE WELL TAKEN CARE OF.
AND WE SPEND AN INORDINATE AMOUNT OF TIME TRYING TO MAKE
SURE THAT THE FILLMORE DISTRICT IS FURTHER A ANNIHILATED.
AND I USE THAT WORD VERY SPECIFICALLY.
>> ELLA HILL HUTCH IS A STAPLE IN THE COMMUNITY.
>> IT HAS BEEN THERE FOR QUITE A LONG TIME AND IT HAS SERVED
MANY COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND TRANSPARENCY SEEMS TO BE
VERY LOST TO THE POLITICIANS IN THIS CITY.
>> I THINK IT IS DISRESPECTFUL .
I THINK IT IS DISINGENUOUS TO HAVE CONVERSATIONS ABOUT THE
CARE OF BLACK SAN FRANCISCO. WHILE PARTICIPATING IN BACKROOM
DEALS AND MEETINGS THAT DO NOT INVOLVE THE COMMUNITY, I AM
ASKING THAT YOU ALL SPECIFICALLY OUR SUPERVISOR FOR
THE FILM OUR DISTRICT TAKE THIS SERIOUSLY.
>> IT IS NOT A JOKE. I KNOW THAT MANY OF YOU DO NOT
FREQUENT OR LIVE IN THE COMMUNITY.
>> BUT THE SAME CARE AND ATTENTION THAT YOU GIVE TO
YOUR PERSONAL LIVES AND TO THE DISTRICTS THAT YOU ARE
REPRESENT DO SO FOR THE FILLMORE DISTRICT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> MY NAME IS SOLILOQUY BACHELOR.
>> ABOLITIONIST. SOCIAL JUSTICE FIGHTER FOR MY
PEOPLE FOR MY NATION TO MAKE A BETTER HUMANITY.
I'M HERE JUST TO INFORM THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS OF A
LYNCHING WHICH IS ALSO CALLED A HANGING.
>> AUGUST THE 25TH OF LAST YEAR .
CARL RAY ABERNATHY WAS FOUND HANGING ON A TREE ON YOSEMITE
STREET IN BAYVIEW. HUNTERS POINT.
>> WE MET WITH THE POLICE COMMISSION.
I AM THE POWER OF ATTORNEY FOR THE FAMILY.
WE PRESENTED ALL OF THE EVIDENCE.
THE CORONER'S OFFICE HAD STATED THAT IT WAS A SUICIDE.
>> SOMEONE WHO SAW THE BODY ABOUT 11 P.M..
STATED THAT WHEN HE CALLED 911 HE WAS A HISPANIC WHO DIDN'T
SPEAK ENGLISH AND HE STATED THAT 911 DISPATCHER TOLD HIM TO
CUT THE BODY DOWN. >> WE FOUND THAT STRANGE FOR
THE 911 CALLER TO TELL A PASSERBY TO CUT THE BODY DOWN.
>> SO THE SISTER SENT A LETTER TO 911 DISPATCHER REQUESTING
FOR THE AUDIO. 911 SAID THAT THEY DENIED HER
THAT SHE COULD NOT HAVE IT FOR PRIVATE REASONS.
>> WE ALSO HAVE A PICTURES THAT I SHOWED THE POLICE COMMISSION.
THIS HAS BEEN GIVEN OVER TO THE POLICE CHIEF JUST AS WELL
IN THE POLICE COMMISSION SHOWING A POSSIBILITY THAT THE
MAN'S CAR WAS CONFISCATED AND OF IT WAS A POSSIBILITY
THAT HE WAS HUNG ACTUALLY HELD TRAPPED IN HIS CAR.
>> ACCORDING TO THE STRAPS, WHICH IS EVIDENCE A WOMAN
PASSED BY AND SAID THAT SHE HAD SAW THE BODY ON THE GROUND
FIRST. SHE THOUGHT IT WAS A BAG OF
CLOTHING AND FOUND OUT IT WAS A BODY THERE.
ALSO THERE WAS A WITNESS TO HIS FORMER HOME.
A WITNESS STATED THAT SHE HEARD TWO MEN FIGHTING AND THEN SHE
FOUND OUT HE WAS DEAD. >> SO I JUST THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER WELCOME REV HER
NAME IS BROWN. AS A MEMBER FORMER MEMBER OF
THE BOARD, YOU'RE BEING GRANTED PRIVILEGE OF THE FLOOR.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. MR. PRESIDENT, MEMBERS OF THIS
AUGUST BODY I RISE TO SAY AS PASTOR EMERITUS OF THE HISTORIC
THIRD BAPTIST CHURCH OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I MUST USE THE WORDS OF THE LATE LANGSTON HUGHES.
>> I SWEAR TO THE LORD I STILL CAN'T SEE WHY DEMOCRACY MEANS
EVERYBODY BUT ME IN THE COURT. MY FRIENDS.
>> THERE HAS BEEN TOO MUCH OF AN ASSAULT AND AN INSULT TO THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY. MORE SPECIFICALLY IN THE
FILLMORE. >> PREVIOUS SPEAKERS SPOKE OF
THE ISSUE AT LARGE AND AROUND THAT ISSUE THAT MATTER.
THERE HAS NOT BEEN DUE PROCESS AND BLATANT DISRESPECT BUT OF
THE INSTITUTIONS THAT ARE ADJACENT TO THAT FACILITY
NAMELY FREDERICK DOUGLASS HAYNES HOUSING DEVELOPMENT,
FRIENDSHIP VILLAGE, FREEDOM WEST L BETHEL ARMS AND NOW
BETHEL TERRACE RAH AND MILLER AND MY FRIENDS, I DO BELIEVE
THAT WE HAVE A RULE THAT WHENEVER THERE IS MADE A PLAN
FOR CONSTRUCTION, A NEW ACTIVITY IN A COMMUNITY THAT IS
GIVEN DUE NOTICE AND DUE PROCESS FOR THE CITIZENRY TO BE
INFORMED WHAT IS TO BE TAKE PLACE.
>> I SAY WITHOUT FEAR OF CONTRADICTION MR. PRESIDENT,
MEMBERS OF THIS BOARD WE HAVE NOT RECEIVED DUE PROCESS.
THEREFORE WE HAVE BEEN DISRESPECTED, DISSED
AND DIVIDED AND I DON'T THINK THAT YOU WILL FEEL TO HAVE IT
ABOUT IN ABOUT WHO WOULD MAKE AN ASSAULT ON YOUR HUMANITY.
AND I SUBMIT TO YOU THAT IS HAPPENING IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. IT IS HAPPENING IN THE FILLMORE
AND I WONDER WHEN IS SUCH GOING TO STOP?
>> JOHN STEINBECK AND THE GRAPES OF WRATH SAID I WONDER
HOW MANY PEOPLE IN MY LIFETIME HAVE I JUST LOOKED AT BUT DID
NOT SEE MY FRIENDS? IT IS HIGH TIME THAT IN THE
CITY OF COUNTY IN THIS COUNTY THAT THE BODY POLITIC STOP.
>> JUST LOOKING AT BLACK FOLKS AS BEING TOOLS AND THINGS
AND SEE THEM AS BEING A MEMBERS OF THE HUMAN FAMILY.
>> THANK YOU, REVEREND BROWN. ARE THERE ANY OTHER INDIVIDUALS
WHO WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> SEEING NONE. MR. PRESIDENT, PUBLIC COMMENT
IS NOW CLOSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS.
>> ITEMS 40 THROUGH 59 TOGETHER ITEMS 40 THROUGH 50 NINE WERE
INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST APPEARANCE. ANY SUPERVISOR MAY REQUIRE
RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. AND MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE REMAINING BALANCE ON ITEMS 40 THROUGH 58
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN. HI GENTLEMEN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
SHERRELL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WANG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I THERE
TONIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED PLEASE
CALL ITEM 50 NINE YES ITEM 59 IS A MOTION TO DIRECT THE CLERK
OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO SCHEDULE A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE ON JUNE 16TH 2026 AT 3:00 PM FOR MEMBERS OF THE BOARD TO
CONSIDER THE RESOLUTION AUTHORIZING THE DIRECTOR OF
TRANSPORTATION TO ENTER INTO A LOAN AGREEMENT WITH THE
METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION AS LENDER FOR SAN
FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY PUBLIC
TRANSIT OPERATING PURPOSES UP TO A MAXIMUM PRINCIPAL AMOUNT
OF 200 MILLION FOR A 12 YEAR TERM FROM JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH
JUNE 3RD, 2028. >> THE PROPOSED MOCA.
THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT MANDELL MAN FOR PUTTING THIS ON
THE AGENDA. WE WILL HEAR THIS AS A
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE NEXT WEEK.
I JUST WANTED TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO A BUNCH OF FOLKS
WHO MADE THIS HAPPEN. THIS OF COURSE IS A LOAN THAT
WE'RE GETTING FROM THE STATE TO TRY THIS OVER UNTIL WE CAN HAVE
OTHER SOURCES OF INCOME TO SAVE OUR PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION
SYSTEMS REGIONALLY. FIRST I WANT TO THANK SUPERB I
AM SENATORS WEINER AND IRENE FOR ALL OF THEIR WORK.
NANCY CALL ALREADY AT THE GOVERNOR'S OFFICE WHO DID MOST
OF THE HEAVY LIFTING IN FIGURING OUT TERMS FOR THIS
LOAN AND AMOUNTS. I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE STAFF
AT THE METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION FOR
DOING A LOT OF THE NEGOTIATING OF THE HEAVY LIFTING.
OUR OWN TO STAFF IS ESPECIALLY AT JESSE KAYLOR AND TILLY CHANG
AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST ALICIA JOHN BAPTIST AT THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE WHO DID LATE NIGHTS IN LOTS OF LOBBYING WITH ALL
SORTS OF FOLKS INCLUDING THE GOVERNOR'S OFFICE.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH COLLEAGUES FOR BEING WILLING TO HEAR THIS.
THAT'S THE COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE NEXT WEEK.
BUT I WANTED TO SAY THANK YOU SO MUCH TO ALL THE STAFF TO
MAKE IT HAPPEN IN ALL OUR PARTNERS REGIONALLY AND AT THE
STATE. >> THANK YOU AND THANK YOU FOR
YOUR WORK AS OUR CHAIR AND MTC REP.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION AND THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> WE DO NOT HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS.
WOULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
YES. TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL.
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHAN AND THE ENTIRE BOARD FOR THE
LATE MR. KEN JONES, DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US
TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
WE ARE ADJOURNED